<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[SAFETAG - RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[Create custom Safetag guides for your needs]]></description><link>https://safetag.org</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 14:24:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[2021 Organizational Security Village Day 4]]></title><description><![CDATA[Yesterday, Internews closed out our second Organizational Security Village! The event brought together security auditors, digital security…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2021-organizational-security-village-day-4</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2021-organizational-security-village-day-4</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 11:37:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, Internews closed out our second &lt;strong&gt;Organizational Security Village&lt;/strong&gt;! The event brought together security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners for a four-day program of over 25 community-led sessions exploring major themes in organizational security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions on Day 4 focused on approaches to OrgSec, OrgSec in practice, responding to advanced threats, and an introduction to digital forensics. Highlights from Day 4 of the OrgSec Village included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A panel conversation with organizational security practitioners working in the MENA region.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A session focused on how teams are applying organizational security practices in situations that are volatile and unpredictable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An exploration of the challenges associated with and tactics for fighting back against online harassment of female journalists.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An overview of findings from research conducted in Eastern Europe and Eurasia on the state of digital security helpers in the region.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A session highlighting the process of incident response and investigations in small and medium-sized civil society organizations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An introduction to malicious document analysis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A discussion on government espionage in Mexico targeting human rights defenders, activists and journalists.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The second part of a discussion on how to make our assessments more effective by better understanding our roles as assessors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key takeaways from the discussions included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the MENA region many organizations lack internal IT support and are also subjected to government surveillance and advanced phishing attacks.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;There are few IT professionals willing to work with civil society organizations, likely as a result of the low pay in comparison to private sector work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When providing digital security support in volatile or unpredictable environments, practitioners must first ensure the physical, mental and emotional wellbeing of the communities with which they are working.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;It can be challenging to introduce new digital security behaviors when people are handling trauma and living in fear. In cases such as these, trust is just as important as expertise.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is a clear correlation between female journalists&apos; online safety and their psychological well being.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Women who experience online harassment tend to suffer from anxiety, shame, and other mental health challenges. A useful first step is helping women understand that they are not alone in this experience nor responsible for what happened to them. Building a culture of awareness of online harassment is crucial to be able to effectively combat these attacks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital security helpers in Eastern Europe and Eurasia are overstressed, overworked, and underpaid.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Research shows that donors need to invest in community building and capacity-building activities (such as skill-shares and mentorship), while also funding rest and recuperation for those providing support on the ground. It is also critical that funders remain flexible and allow local partners to adapt to meet needs and ensure that support is sustainable long-term.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital security champions embedded within organizations can play an important role in incident response and ground-level forensics.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;These individuals can serve as a first point of contact within an organization, gathering relevant data about the incident and conducting initial triage to confirm if the content is malicious.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are many different workflows to identify whether or not a file is malicious.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;These processes can be crucial at the triage stage of providing digital security support. The advice to “not open suspicious files” is not realistic for some professions, such as journalists, who rely on information that is often shared by individuals they do not know directly. While some antivirus software can help detect malicious files, some individuals or groups may be targeted by custom malware which would not be detected by antivirus. Utilizing more advanced workflows to analyze documents will allow you to spot malicious content that may be embedded into the file. Additionally, there are tools like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.circl.lu/projects/CIRCLean/&quot;&gt;CIRClean&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://dangerzone.rocks/&quot;&gt;Dangerzone&lt;/a&gt; which can be used to open suspicious files.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you find evidence that individuals have been compromised, you must be mindful of how you present the findings back to them.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Reporting back to community members about your findings can help build and maintain trust. It is also important to share actionable recommendations based on the findings that will help the targets minimize the damage of this attack and mitigate risks in the future.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Often there is a disconnect between organizations receiving support and organizational security practitioners.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Organizations generally are looking for a more immediate “fix” or one-time solution while security practitioners are hoping to encourage long-term behavior changes.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;To help mitigate these sometimes competing goals, it is critical that everyone involved in an audit is open and ready to listen to others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you to everyone who participated in the OrgSec Village this week! You can find summaries for each day of programming &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/posts/&quot;&gt;here on the blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[2021 Organizational Security Village Day 3]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internews continued the virtual Organizational Security Village today with community-led sessions targeting security auditors, digital…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2021-organizational-security-village-day-3</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2021-organizational-security-village-day-3</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 09:59:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Internews continued the virtual Organizational Security Village today with community-led sessions targeting security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions on Day 3 explored OrgSec in Practice. Highlights included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An interactive session discussing the ways and sources through which we can learn and share more about threats affecting at-risk groups and individuals.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A deep look at the main issues that OrgSec and other projects encounter at the planning and implementation stages, and what we can do to minimise such problems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The first part of a wider discussion on how to make our assessments more effective by better understanding our needs and those of our stakeholders.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An exploration of the various adaptations OrgSec practitioners have deployed during the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A collaborative session to identify emerging challenges and map strategies and best practices for providing remote training of trainers (ToTs).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A review of core principles for ensuring sustainability in security projects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A round of feedback sessions offering design and UX support for tools and resources supporting the OrgSec community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key takeaways from the discussions included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not that easy to access threat intelligence.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Much of it is segmented and fragmented, or hidden behind paywalls.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Additionally, there’s little threat intelligence that specifically focuses on civil society targets. As such, the community has many different ways of accessing it - from places such as social media sites and YouTube videos to results of forensic investigations and incident response. We need to invest more time and effort into trainings around malware research, intelligence sharing, threat analysis, and pentesting.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our OrgSec projects must be flexible and adaptable.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;It’s very common for project priorities to shift once you’re a couple of months in. As such, it’s crucial to be able to change the project’s plans midway through, communicate actively about this with partners and donors, and focus on targets and indicators that are grounded in the needs of the local community. Trust is key to any project, but especially important for those which need to adapt their scope and priorities - as such, it’s crucial to listen to and engage partners, donors, and team members at every stage of the project implementation process.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the main reasons people don’t pursue more secure workflows is that they stop them from simply getting their job done&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;As such, it’s crucial for our security to not just be prescriptive but also empathetic and focused on listening to the needs of everybody within your organization. Everybody, including the security champions, will come from a different background and perspective.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the context of COVID-19, OrgSec practitioners must be flexible in their approaches and be prepared to pivot quickly during engagements.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Most people are experiencing additional trauma as a result of the pandemic, which can impact their ability to engage and increases the need for prioritizing wellness during all engagements. From providing funding support to cover data costs to extending virtual trainings or assessments across a longer period of time, it’s often the OrgSec practitioner who needs to adapt to accommodate participants who are already overwhelmed with their usual tasks and assignments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is important to make an online Training of Trainers (ToT) as interactive and engaging as possible.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;This can be achieved by hosting a series of shorter engagements over a longer period of time instead of one long session, utilizing games or scenarios to facilitate learning, assigning “homework” or group projects that allow participants to practice, and inviting participants to connect and share on collaborative tools and platforms.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building trust, establishing community ownership, and using tools that will live beyond the life of a project are several strategies to help ensure the sustainability of your security project.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;It can also be useful to diversify providers (making sure the burden of community security does not fall on one single individual or organization) and to focus on establishing processes that encourage long-term behavior change, ongoing sharing of threat data, and prevention efforts in addition to incident response.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our final day of sessions will focus on OrgSec in Practice, Advanced Threats, and more! Check back here for the daily recap!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[2021 Organizational Security Village Day 2]]></title><description><![CDATA[During the second day of Internews’ virtual Organizational Security Village we continued exploring OrgSec tools and resources, while also…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2021-organizational-security-village-day-2</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2021-organizational-security-village-day-2</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 12:24:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;During the second day of Internews’ virtual &lt;strong&gt;Organizational Security Village&lt;/strong&gt; we continued exploring OrgSec tools and resources, while also beginning to look at diverse approaches to OrgSec adopted by practitioners in the community. Highlights from Day 2 of the OrgSec Village included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An interactive session aimed at deconstructing resistance to change in organizations adopting digital security improvements.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An in-depth introduction on how to use Open Source Intelligence (OSINT) tools and techniques to protect yourself from risk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sharing of lessons learned from conducting SAFETAG trainings of auditors on and offline.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An exploration of the ecosystem of tools and resources available to OrgSec practitioners.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An overview of the processes and required resources for launching a non-profit organization that provides digital security support to civil society organizations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key takeaways from the discussions included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By mapping narratives of resistance from organizations adopting digital security and sharing best practices, practitioners will be better prepared to offer creative responses to help motivate organizations to prioritize safety&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;From working with the organization to identify what is important to them (their resources, their networks, etc.), making clear the risk, and outlining the possible security interventions, it’s essential to empower the organization and tailor your approach. Often there is not one single strategy, but rather a combination of mitigations which will help keep the organization safe as they continue their work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be aware of your digital footprint and understand how OSINT may assist you in your own investigations.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;OSINT investigations are often the first step in a targeted attack campaign against an individual or company. Attackers can use this publicly available, legally accessible information (often gathered from social media) against targets. Once you know your digital footprint, you can understand the risks and threats that this information presents to you and your network. Armed with this information you can develop defensive strategies to mitigate physical or online attacks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When conducting a training for new SAFETAG auditors, it’s important to make it a gradual process instead of a one-off training.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Be sure to allow space for new auditors to roleplay various scenarios, conduct their first audits alongside a more experienced auditor, and receive ongoing mentorship throughout the process. This requires experienced auditors who are embedded in communities and have the time and resources to provide long-term support.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are MANY tools and resources specifically focused on organizational security. Rather than searching for the universal tool that will be relevant for every situation or organization, consider these resources and tools as part of your “toolkit” or “tool box”.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;The tool you select will depend entirely on the organization with which you are working and the specific context.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;In some cases, the tools are meant to complement one another, or can be seen as building blocks as the organization’s security capacity increases.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From lawyers specializing in digital rights to accountants to technologists, each position plays a critical role in creating and maintaining a successful organization offering digital rights and digital security support.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;When designing your organization, prioritize long-term support for your partners and think beyond individual training sessions. This will allow you to track progress over time, provide more holistic support (such as ongoing incident response and threat analysis), and ensure that beneficiaries are implementing the practices and tools you share with them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sessions continue throughout the week focusing on OrgSec in Practice, Advanced Threats, and more. Check back here for the daily recap!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[2021 Organizational Security Village Day 1]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internews is hosting our second virtual Organizational Security Village throughout this week (August 30-September 2)! The event is bringing…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2021-organizational-security-village-day-1</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2021-organizational-security-village-day-1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 10:30:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Internews is hosting our second virtual Organizational Security Village throughout this week (August 30-September 2)! The event is bringing together security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners for a four-day program of over 25 community-led sessions exploring four major themes in organizational security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions on Day 1 centred around various OrgSec tools and resources. Highlights from Day 1 of the OrgSec village included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A conversation on how to bridge the gap between open source tool developers and users to improve usability and accessibility.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A tour of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rarenet.org/&quot;&gt;RaReNet &lt;/a&gt;(Rapid Response Network) and CiviCERT’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalfirstaid.org/&quot;&gt;Digital First Aid Kit&lt;/a&gt; (DFAK).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An introduction to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/&quot;&gt;new SAFETAG interface&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An overview of the recently released &lt;a href=&quot;https://conexo.org/project/rawrr/&quot;&gt;RAWRR&lt;/a&gt;, an offline multiplatform and easy-to-use tool for security evaluation report generation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A preview of NDI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://cso.cyberhandbook.org/&quot;&gt;Cybersecurity Handbook for Civil Society Organizations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key takeaways from the discussions included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessibility work goes beyond UX/UI design&lt;/strong&gt;. When it comes to creating feedback loops between users and developers, it’s important to not just include UX/UI designers but also the developers themselves. It’s crucial to involve all of those who are working on putting together the infrastructure users rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civil Society Organizations (CSOs) are facing increasingly complex cybersecurity threats, which require solutions beyond traditional cybersecurity trainings&lt;/strong&gt;. CSOs tend to be reactive when it comes to organizational security and often scramble to find solutions in the face of a crisis. While traditional digital security trainings are helpful in better preparing CSOs, they often fail to fully address the challenges of emerging cyber threats, offensive technologies, and organizational complexity. Scenario-based and tailored resources may allow CSOs to be more proactive in anticipating and addressing potential threats they might encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider (and involve) your target audience when designing OrgSec tools and resources&lt;/strong&gt;. If possible, deploy a co-design process or request ongoing feedback from trusted members of the community. Plan and design so that localization is an integral part of the process. Be prepared to iterate on your tool or resource in efforts to make it as useful as possible for those who need it most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join us for more sessions throughout the week on Approaches to OrgSec, OrgSec in Practice, Advanced Threats, and more!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Announcing the 2021 Organizational Security Village]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internews is excited to announce that we will be hosting our second virtual Organizational Security Village from August 30-September 2, 202…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2021-07-20-announcing-2021-orgsec-village</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2021-07-20-announcing-2021-orgsec-village</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/title_osv2021.png&quot; alt=&quot;OrgSec Village - August 30-September 2, 2021&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internews is excited to announce that we will be hosting our second virtual Organizational Security Village from &lt;strong&gt;August 30-September 2, 2021&lt;/strong&gt;. This event will bring together security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners for a four-day program highlighting community-led sessions exploring organizational security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Virtual Village Format&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on feedback from the community following &lt;a href=&quot;https://internews.org/?s=orgsec%20village&quot;&gt;last year’s event&lt;/a&gt;, we will retain the same format, hosting live sessions during four consecutive days. Each session will last approximately 50 minutes with a short break in between sessions. We will share a schedule and additional information on each session prior to the event. You are invited to join as many or as few sessions as you would like!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recognize that some may not be able to join due to timing or prior engagements. To ensure that everyone has the opportunity to contribute in some way, non-attributed, editable notes from each session will be made available to all those who register for the event.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Registration and CoC&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please let us know you will be attending by registering here no later than &lt;strong&gt;August 23&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.office.com/r/YZBn5JwPuK&quot;&gt;https://forms.office.com/r/YZBn5JwPuK&lt;/a&gt;  We ask that you register even if you only plan to attend a few days or sessions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event access details will only be shared with registered participants.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please also complete the registration form if you are not able to join the live sessions but would like to review notes or contribute asynchronously.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This event will follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://usable.tools/coc/&quot;&gt;USABLE Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Session Proposals&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Community members are invited to submit a session proposal via the form below. All sessions will last approximately 50 minutes and breakout functionality will be available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Session Proposals: &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.office.com/r/5Piqqab7mX&quot;&gt;https://forms.office.com/r/5Piqqab7mX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Session proposals are due by &lt;strong&gt;August 4&lt;/strong&gt;. Applicants will be notified of selection no later than &lt;strong&gt;August 13&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SAFETAG’s New Interface]]></title><description><![CDATA[In addition to developing SAFETAG’s new visual identity, Internews has partnered with Development Seed and J++ to build a new SAFETAG…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2021-06-04-new-interface</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2021-06-04-new-interface</guid><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/newinterfaceblogcover.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image with title SAFETAG’s New Interface&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to developing SAFETAG’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/posts/2021-06-04-new-visual-identity&quot;&gt;new visual identity&lt;/a&gt;, Internews has partnered with &lt;a href=&quot;https://developmentseed.org/&quot;&gt;Development Seed&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://jplusplus.org/en/&quot;&gt;J++&lt;/a&gt; to build a new SAFETAG interface that is easier to use and more accessible for both new and experienced auditors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Playlist Creation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new interface allows auditors to generate “playlists,” or collections of audit activities tailored to a specific type of organization or risk environment. These customized and shareable playlists can be stored for future reference or shared with other auditors working in similar contexts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the creation of a playlist was possible previously with SAFETAG, the process was complex and difficult for most auditors, particularly those that were new to SAFETAG. The new interface allows auditors, both experienced and new,  to create a playlist by simply selecting the activities they would like to include. Auditors can use metadata to filter through different activities based on the method, organization size, whether it can be done remotely, and more. Once selected, the playlist generator creates a unique URL for the playlist, and can also be used to compile the selected activities into a downloadable PDF, which can be saved or shared with fellow auditors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/interface_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of website with blue safetag logo in a box at the top, rectangular buttons that say &amp;#x27;Methods,&amp;#x27; &amp;#x27;Activities,&amp;#x27; &amp;#x27;Org Size,&amp;#x27; &amp;#x27;Approaches,&amp;#x27; and &amp;#x27;Remote Options&amp;#x27; which display drop down menus for user selection. On the left there is a rectangle that says &amp;#x27;Method: Reconnaisance&amp;#x27; with the sub-heading &amp;#x27;automated reconnaissance&amp;#x27; selected. On the right there is another rectangle that says &amp;#x27;selected SAFETAG Guide content with a &amp;#x27;download PDF Guide&amp;#x27; button in blue.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Display of Methods and Activities&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using SAFETAG’s new visual identity, Development Seed and J++ helped us create a site that not only allows auditors to build customized playlists, but also organizes SAFETAG’s methods and activities in a format that is much easier to understand and use. After receiving feedback from the community, we knew that understanding the guide and where to begin as a new auditor was one of the top challenges faced by the auditor community. The new interface allows auditors to explore each method individually, with the necessary information and activities displayed on its own page, as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/interface_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a SAFETAG method page for the &amp;#x27;Organizational Policy Review&amp;#x27; with subheadings and descriptions for &amp;#x27;Summary&amp;#x27;, &amp;#x27;Purpose,&amp;#x27; and &amp;#x27;Guiding Questions&amp;#x27;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Contributing Content&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new interface allows auditors to directly edit and contribute new content via Netlify CMS, a process much simpler and easier to use than the previous method done exclusively through GitHub. The Netlify CMS portal will allow both new and experienced auditors to edit and contribute without much Git experience required, reducing the barrier to entry for many SAFETAG users. SAFETAG remains a fully open source project and all source code from this tech staff as well as the contents of the guide can be accessed on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/tree/guide-source&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/interface_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a webpage with &amp;#x27;Collections,&amp;#x27; &amp;#x27;Activities&amp;#x27; and a &amp;#x27;sort by&amp;#x27; filter menu. Dark gray rectangle button with the words &amp;#x27;New Activity&amp;#x27; is on the right side of the page.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Check it out!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can explore the new and improved site &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.safetag.org/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;! Go ahead and try the &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/admin&quot;&gt;new content contribution feature&lt;/a&gt; and please share any feedback on the site with us at info [at] safetag [dot] org.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SAFETAG’s New Visual Identity!]]></title><description><![CDATA[Over the past year, Internews has worked closely with Tafka Co-op, Development Seed, J++ and the SAFETAG community to create a new visual…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2021-06-04-new-visual-identity</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2021-06-04-new-visual-identity</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/newvizblogcover.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image with title SAFETAG&apos;s New Visual Identity&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, Internews has worked closely with &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencollective.com/tafka-co-op&quot;&gt;Tafka Co-op&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://developmentseed.org/&quot;&gt;Development Seed&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jplusplus.org/en/&quot;&gt;J++&lt;/a&gt; and the SAFETAG community to create a new visual identity and web interface that is more user-friendly, interactive, and community-focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through a series of open calls, a community survey, and input from Internews partners, we received &lt;a href=&quot;https://usable.tools/blog/2020-09-24-communityfeedback/&quot;&gt;feedback from over 25 SAFETAG auditors&lt;/a&gt; around the globe used to inform the new design. The feedback we received made it clear that one of the most important values of SAFETAG is the community-driven focus and we hope that this new visual identity and web interface encapsulates that aspect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;New logo and design assets&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/logosmall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blue rectangle outline with the word &amp;#x27;safetag&amp;#x27; in blue on the left, and a filled in blue square on the right with a white lock and a circle on top inside the square.&quot;&gt;
As part of the new visual identity, Tafka Co-op worked with Internews and the broader SAFETAG community to update and/or create the following assets:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Updated logo, shown above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New color palette&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New iconography set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New customizable graphics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New accessibility guidance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sample presentation slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sample print configurations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of our priorities when redesigning the SAFETAG interface was to make the framework more usable. A lot of the feedback received showed that new auditors had trouble following the framework, knowing where to begin, how many activities to use in their audit, etc. In response to this, we developed new iconography which will help guide auditors through the interface and framework based on their needs. A total of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.figma.com/file/ATTHbHSGthsteeXP4gnlxF/Safetag-%E2%86%92-Branding-system?node-id=55%3A0&quot;&gt;20 icons&lt;/a&gt; were developed, however the three that will be used to represent each type of activity are shown below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/TRI.png&quot; alt=&quot;Technical: Blue and Orange graphic. The blue line is behind the orange line with two open semi-circle at the top left and bottom right of the line. Orange line goes across from bottom left to top right in the shape of an X across the blue. Text below the graphic reads &amp;#x27;Technical.&amp;#x27; Interpersonal: Blue and Orange graphic with zig-zagged open semi-circles in alternating blue and orange colors horizontally across the middle, with two blue dots at the top above the blue open semi-circles, and one orange dot at the bottom below the orange open semi-circle. Text below the graphic reads &amp;#x27;Interpersonal&amp;#x27;. Research: Graphic shows a blue magnifying glass made of a basic circle and line, with an orange vertical line, blue square, and orange triangle on the inside of the circle. Text below graphic reads &amp;#x27;Research.&amp;#x27;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each SAFETAG audit is custom-built to the needs of the organization which is being audited. Designed with this in mind, the logo and all icons were built using a series of shapes and colors, or elements, arranged to represent each activity. These elements are used as building blocks, combining to form each icon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/shapes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Basic shapes graphic: Graphic shows, from left to right, a blue circle, a blue open semi-circle, an orange triangle, blue square, and orange circle arranged vertically, a vertical blue rectangle, an orange open circle, and a horizontal blue rectangle. Text below the graphic reads &amp;#x27;Basic shapes are configured to represent methods and activities such as Physical Assessment, Responsive Support, and Organizational Device Usage. Physical Assessment Icon: Blue rectangle with a small graphic of a person on top, with an orange circle, a blue square, and an orange triangle arranged horizontally inside the rectangle. Text reads Physical Assessment Icon. Responsive Support Icon: Blue checkmark with an orange triangle at the top of the shorter end, and an orange circle at the top of the longer end on the right. Text reads Responsive Support Icon. Organizational Device Usage Icon: Blue brackets with an orange circle, blue square, orange triangle, blue triangle, orange circle, and blue square arranged in two lines inside of the brackets. Text reads Organizational Device Usage Icon.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Basic shapes are configured to represent methods and activities such as Physical Assessment, Responsive Support, and Organizational Device Usage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individually, each shape represents a specific element of SAFETAG (such as data, organization, individual, etc.), and when configured together, represent a larger concept or method (such as Organizational Device Usage or Physical Assessment).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are prioritizing a community-driven approach by hosting these assets on Figma, a platform that is free to use and allows full customization of the design assets. You can explore the icons and customizable design assets &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.figma.com/file/ATTHbHSGthsteeXP4gnlxF/Safetag-%E2%86%92-Branding-system?node-id=29%3A0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;*.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;New SAFETAG Interface&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the new visual identity, we have been working with Development Seed and J++ to build a new SAFETAG interface that is easier to use and more accessible for both new and experienced auditors. Learn more about the new interface &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/posts/2021-06-04-new-interface&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;*A full documentation package with guidance on how to navigate the design assets is forthcoming.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to implement a remote SAFETAG audit: A step by step guide.]]></title><description><![CDATA[Since the pandemic, the information security community has been experimenting with how to make security auditing and risk assessments safer…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-12-04-remote-audit-steps</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-12-04-remote-audit-steps</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/RemoteSteps.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image with title How to implement a remote SAFETAG audit: A step by step guide.&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the pandemic, the information security community has been experimenting with how to make security auditing and risk assessments safer, adapting them to be remote where possible. This is the third blog post in a series exploring how we can improve the remote &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG&quot;&gt;SAFETAG&lt;/a&gt; auditing experience, capturing guidance that will be useful for other security practitioners using the SAFETAG framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Our Goals Don’t Change Simply Because We’re Remote&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re using the SAFETAG framework or a standard like &lt;a href=&quot;https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/Legacy/SP/nistspecialpublication800-30r1.pdf&quot;&gt;NIST&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iso.org/isoiec-27001-information-security.html&quot;&gt;ISO 27001/2&lt;/a&gt;, the key to a good information security assessment starts with understanding what the organization values most. This is the reason we have security in the first place. If we do not understand what the organization is trying to protect, we will not be able to recommend appropriate and effective mitigations or controls to improve their security.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The challenge we often face as practitioners is eliciting this information from the organization quickly and accurately. Simply asking an organization what they value often does not result in the most accurate of information. It is the auditor’s job to read between the lines, ask the right questions, infer, and follow-up to develop a list of “assets”, or things the organization is trying to protect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, this is foundational to the approach of the remote risk assessment using the SAFETAG framework. It is important to remember the approach to SAFETAG can be broken down into three important bodies of work, referred to as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/2018/08/16/SAFETAGStories-dropbox.html&quot;&gt;TRI Approach&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpersonal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the remote auditing context, it can be tempting to reduce the amount of time dedicated to the Interpersonal type of work such as the interactive threat or process mapping exercises. However, practitioners should resist avoiding the interactive modules, as oftentimes these are the most fruitful and illuminating. Instead, pivoting and reimagining modules is better than eliminating them altogether.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Minimum Viable Audit vs Remote Audit&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest challenges we’ve faced as we’ve had to transition and adapt our audits to be more remote-friendly is that we didn’t want to lose the fiercely pragmatic and capacity-driven nature of the SAFETAG audit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;So how does the Minimum Viable Audit come into play?&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through our remote auditing experience, we’ve tried to keep as much of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/blob/master/en/index.mva.md&quot;&gt;Minimum Viable Audit&lt;/a&gt; components as possible to ensure we’re holistically assessing the organization. In a remote setting, there are often more constraints due to the realities and contexts you’re working in, but there are still core components of SAFETAG that should be attempted across the three areas: Technical, Research, and Interpersonal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In some instances, the team had to reimagine a module based on the function rather than the form. For example, the Process Mapping exercise was difficult for us to conduct remotely, and we pivoted instead to one-on-one interviews to get the same information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Implementing Your Remote Audit&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike face-to-face audits where in-person time with the organization can be used as a great way to divide up the stages of the process, in remote assessments, the timeline can feel more lengthy and less clear. This includes the end of the audit, which can feel blurry and less definitive since the activities can follow a completely different timeline compared to more “traditional” engagements.  In this context, planning becomes key, so we can have a complete picture of all the activities that will be conducted and their status, given many of them will seem to have less defined boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another consideration is that people frequently shift their attention to different kinds of tasks with different people in the remote work dynamic. In this context, it&apos;s harder to have staff engaged in the same way you would have previously when in a room together focused on an activity, like a risk matrix construction or a data mapping exercise. Because of this, it is important to aim for concrete interactions and reduce unnecessary synchronous group activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One way to address this is to very clearly communicate and classify the activities by the involvement of the organization and its staff, including the specific amount of time required. By communicating this to the organization, you will come to a better shared understanding of which activities can be done independently and which will need organization participation. Examples might include deploying a capacity assessment survey that can be completed asynchronously instead of individual one-on-one interviews with the entire staff. The survey would still take some amount of staff time, but likely less than the interview.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With all of this in mind, a general workflow to implement a remote audit could look something like the following, but should ultimately be built upon the realities and constraints with which you’re dealing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare and plan:&lt;/strong&gt; Determine and communicate the activities that will be done without staff members participating such as open source intelligence (OSINT) gathering, Reconnaissance, Web Application Testing, as well as others which will require the attention of people in the organization. In our experience, remote audits have spanned across a much longer time frame. It is important to immediately start logistics coordination on all exercises you want to do synchronously with the organization. You should also aim to integrate into the initial activities any possible information gathering about the organization’s threat model and data interactions usually obtained in physical activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start your asynchronous activities:&lt;/strong&gt; Starting these asynchronous activities while coordinating larger or one-on-one meetings can help get the audit process moving forward. Some examples of these activities are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OSINT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../methods/reconnaissance&quot;&gt;Reconnaissance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../activities/web_vulnerability_assessment&quot;&gt;Website Assessment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../activities/policies_review&quot;&gt;Policy Reviews&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../activities/capacity_assessment_cheatsheet&quot;&gt;Capacity Assessment Surveys&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set up common synchronous activities:&lt;/strong&gt; As mentioned throughout the article, we cannot overemphasize being organized when doing everything in a remote setting. There are more logistics, more technological difficulties, and overall more challenges with building  trust when interacting with staff through a screen. Some examples of synchronous activities you may prioritize to complete during your audit include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../activities/interviews&quot;&gt;One-on-One Interviews (rather than Process Mapping)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../activities/remote_asset_valuation&quot;&gt;Data Mapping / Asset Valuation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../activities/threat_identification&quot;&gt;Threat Mapping&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../methods/user_device_assessment&quot;&gt;Remote User Device Assessment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From Process Mapping to Interviews&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When conducting more and more remote SAFETAG audits it became painstakingly apparent that one-on-one interviews would be increasingly important and necessary to capture much of the information from modules previously completed in-person. The team transitioned things like Process Mapping to a one-on-one exercise with as many of the organization’s staff from different departments as possible. While individual interviews may be more time consuming, they also have their benefits. You can build trust quickly while capturing very honest feedback and information to support the organization in their security improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running Remote Virtual Group Exercises&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtual facilitation is tough and will have a learning curve. However, through our experience, exercises like data mapping or threat mapping have been successful with the right tool and right preparation. Reduce the technology burden where possible. Use technologies the organization may already be familiar with and only introduce new tools if needed. A few we’ve used in our experience are Jamboards and Google Sheets (depending on the organization and constraints at hand).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Synthesize:&lt;/strong&gt; With remote audits, where the outcomes are obtained from perhaps a greater mix of activities, it can be challenging to distill into actionable results. However, the same as an on-site audit, one of the primary goals of a remote audit is to have a good and as complete as possible understanding of the organization’s security weaknesses and strengths. We also want to ensure we capture feasible and relevant recommendations. It is important to take the time to review all your notes and artifacts from exercises (especially from the one-on-one interviews, if applicable) and transform them into a holistic and complete picture of the organization to better connect their needs to recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presentation and debrief:&lt;/strong&gt; The virtual debrief and report presentation of findings does not change significantly, since often these are delivered after the in-person audit. However, like any remote presentation or meeting, it can be easier if you have a visual to review with the organization such as top strengths and recommended improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remember, the flow presented above is something that has worked for us. There are of course more ways to implement a remote audit, but we tried to come up with a list of learnings based on our experience thus far. You can find more of our lessons learned here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We understand remote adaptations to the SAFETAG framework can be challenging in a variety of ways for a variety of reasons. However, SAFETAG audits are still possible with a little adaptation and planning. Get creative and think outside the box when it comes to building a fuller and more complete picture of the organization so that your recommendations will address real-world challenges. And remember, if  we’re able to improve our remote audit processes this only helps us reach more organizations in need of security audits, making them more accessible to groups who need them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[8 Tips for Facilitating a Remote Training of SAFETAG Auditors]]></title><description><![CDATA[Over the last few months and as a direct result of the COVID-19 pandemic, the world has had to shift to a fully-remote workflow…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-12-16-8TipsforRemoteToAs</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-12-16-8TipsforRemoteToAs</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/8Tips_RemoteToA.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image with title 8 Tips for Facilitating a Remote Training of SAFETAG Auditors&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months and as a direct result of the COVID-19 pandemic, the world has had to shift to a fully-remote workflow. Organizational security audits and trainings for new SAFETAG auditors are no exception. Thankfully, a few Internews partners have already implemented  remote trainings, and have shared some lessons learned and resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Lessons learned from implementing a fully virtual Training of SAFETAG Auditors:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide multiple methods of engagement for participants.&lt;/strong&gt; In addition to live sessions for the training, assign homework, related podcasts, or asynchronous work that can be completed by participants on their own time. This helps keep participants engaged and allows for more flexibility in their schedules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep the live sessions short (2-3 hours), and spread them over the course of a few weeks.&lt;/strong&gt; Keeping live sessions short, in combination with multiple methods of engagement, will allow participants to maintain engagement without losing focus. Shorter sessions also make it easier for individuals to participate fully as they are able to balance their time and focus on other competing tasks or priorities for the remainder of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduce participants to the platform you will be using for the training.&lt;/strong&gt; Prior to the training (or as one of the first training sessions), show participants how you will be using the platform, and allow time for them to become more familiar with using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose a platform that allows participants to access materials and sessions all in one place.&lt;/strong&gt; For example, one partner used Google Classroom for a 10-day training.This platform allowed participants to see the curricula, complete the homework assignments, listen to podcasts, and join the live sessions all in one place. This makes the experience more organized and it is easier for participants to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When possible, record live sessions and allow participants to access.&lt;/strong&gt; You will likely have some participants with poor internet connection which may prevent them from being able to join the live sessions. By giving participants access to recorded sessions, they will be able to catch up on any missed sessions and continue to participate in the training without falling behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow participants to access training materials and resources even after the training ends.&lt;/strong&gt; Participants have noted that it is useful to be able to continue accessing materials for reference after the training. It is also helpful to be able to reach out to trainers with questions or for any clarifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a group chat for quick updates and outreach during the training.&lt;/strong&gt; Creating a group chat (on Signal or some other tool of your choosing) enables coordination between trainers and participants, and provides a space where trainers can reach everyone quickly with any announcements, questions, or changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reminding participants to read through materials, ask questions, and attempt the assignments is key.&lt;/strong&gt; Not all participants will complete the assignments and attend every session. Remote trainings will often mean that participants are working from their homes, with additional distractions and competing priorities. Reminders can go a long way to increase participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[15 Tips for Conducting Remote SAFETAG Audits]]></title><description><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic has led to a dramatic increase in the need for remote audits and other virtual digital security interventions…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-11-05-13TipsForRemoteAudits</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-11-05-13TipsForRemoteAudits</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/15Tips.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image with title 15 Tips for Conducting Remote SAFETAG Audits&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has led to a dramatic increase in the need for remote audits and other virtual digital security interventions. Auditors are having to adapt their approaches and respond to new security threats and landscapes. In coordination with auditors across the globe, Internews has developed a Remote Audit Playlist, a collection of &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org&quot;&gt;SAFETAG&lt;/a&gt; activities that can be performed remotely under varying conditions from low bandwidth to distributed team scenarios. While remote audits are new for some practitioners, others have been implementing them for years. Below are some of the lessons Internews and our partners have learned while conducting remote SAFETAG audits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building trust is critical, but comes less naturally during remote audits.&lt;/strong&gt; Accept that you will need to address this ‘confidence gap’. Establish trust relationships with senior people or ‘champions’ of the audit in the organization and allow them to introduce you to other participants and interviewees. Use video during online calls (if possible) to make up for the loss of in-person body language. During group calls schedule strategic breaks in the programming or meeting for ice breakers. Sharing your own style and personal way of reporting with participants is also important. This helps to establish a better connection and mutual level of trust. Frequent check-ins can also help you gauge how participants are feeling at any given moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get organized with your remote tooling and processes.&lt;/strong&gt; Start with clear communication and planning with the organization. Ensure they understand what to expect and when. Practice your remote facilitation with the tools and activities you plan to run in your audit. Templatize your data assessment exercise, your semi-structured interviews, your risk mapping activities. Whatever you can do to make things easier to repeat is great to have in your toolbox for next time and helps with keeping things organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow extra time for the full engagement.&lt;/strong&gt; While you may be able to carry out all interviews, group discussions, and technical investigations over the course of a few days when engaging in-person, expect remote engagements to take longer. Most people have a limit to the amount of time they can commit to online calls and may already be overwhelmed with them. Leave sufficient breathing room in your audit schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share a pre-audit survey with staff members.&lt;/strong&gt; An online survey sent to all staff members can help you, as an auditor, find out which members of the organization are most interested in knowing about the security gaps and mitigation strategies. It can also help you identify different user experiences, levels of security practice, and levels of awareness within the organization. Send reminders and enlist the help of senior management or leadership to encourage respondents to complete the survey. Know that not all staff will respond but seek to obtain a key sample of staff such as IT personnel, a mix of technical and non-technical staff, management, and staff in high-risk programmatic positions. Getting a variety of user views and experiences is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When sharing an online form or survey related to baseline best practices, closed-ended questions work best.&lt;/strong&gt; This will keep the survey short and more people are likely to respond. Save the open-ended questions for the interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resist the urge to only do the technical pentesting exercises.&lt;/strong&gt; SAFETAG is made up of a variety of different components, of which only some are technical. The Interpersonal methods are very important to help build your understanding of what the organization values and how they protect them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interweave group, one-on-one, and technical activities.&lt;/strong&gt; Plan an audit strategy which combines key moments of group engagement (for instance an audit kick-off call, risk assessments, team/department meetings, and presentation of preliminary findings) with one-on-one interviews, and technical assessment activities (such as vulnerability assessment, open source intelligence, and network scanning). Remember that the audit process is iterative - as you discover new information from group calls, you will uncover new assets to scan, and add questions to discuss with individual team members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schedule interviews with key staff members to follow-up on survey responses and ask clarifying questions.&lt;/strong&gt; It is best to limit these interviews to one hour, as anything longer than this can feel overwhelming and can be difficult to schedule. Agree on the logistics in advance (i.e. the platform you will use to connect, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Familiarize yourself with the technology that the organization uses prior to the remote audit.&lt;/strong&gt; If you are not yet familiar with the platforms or tools that they use, do some research prior to the audit so that learning about the technology does not take up your limited interview time. Also spend time using the SAFETAG reconnaissance activities to form an independent understanding of their digital footprint and technology used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It can be helpful to share the interview questions and/or checklists prior to the interview.&lt;/strong&gt; This can help staff members understand what to expect and prepare for the interview. Since time is limited, this can help eliminate the need for staff to spend interview time finding answers to your questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a script and an agenda ready to go prior to the meeting.&lt;/strong&gt; In person, it is easier to go with the flow and dive into topics as they come up, but unstructured conversations online are much more difficult to navigate. It is helpful to have a plan and a structure to follow during the remote assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare for internet connectivity issues.&lt;/strong&gt; At times there will be challenges with internet connectivity from both the interviewee and the auditor. In order to set yourself up for a successful remote audit interview and user device assessment, consider the internet connection available before proceeding with the task. Also, have a clear plan of action established in case you are disconnected. For example, specify what communication channel you will follow-up on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give staff members an indication of what to expect.&lt;/strong&gt; Before remote interactions, let them know you will be looking into their device and browser. This will give participants the opportunity to close out of any windows they do not want to share. Also be sure to flag any tools you may be using during the interview (such as TeamViewer). Explain what the tool is capable of and provide instructions for installation before the interview and deinstallation once the interview is complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Different organizations will have different challenges.&lt;/strong&gt; Online assessments are easier for smaller organizations. Simpler infrastructures have fewer potential issues and are typically easier to manage. For organizations that are already accustomed to a remote-work culture, online assessments come more naturally. For larger organizations with customized systems, remote audits can be more complicated, and in some cases impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make it fun!&lt;/strong&gt; Use interactive approaches to engage participants especially in group calls. Consider using shared pads, polls, quizzes, whiteboards, and other visual simultaneous collaboration tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Responding to COVID-19: A Transition to Remote SAFETAG Audits]]></title><description><![CDATA[For the past several years, the SAFETAG community has explored what remote support could be provided to organizations in situations where…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-10-28-RemoteTransition</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-10-28-RemoteTransition</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/RemoteTransition.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image with title Responding to COVID-19: A Transition to Remote SAFETAG Audits&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past several years, the SAFETAG community has explored what remote support could be provided to organizations in situations where the auditor cannot travel to the organization or meet with staff in-person. There are also organizations which have distributed teams operating fully remotely or from multiple physical locations, making it difficult or impossible to conduct in-person audits. Though these conversations around remote audits began years ago, the recent COVID-19 pandemic has reignited discussions and led to a dramatic increase in the need for remote audits and other virtual digital security interventions. Civil society organizations around the world have been forced to migrate to a fully-remote workflow. This transition, in addition to creating new security challenges, has also required auditors to adapt the way in which they are providing support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internews, in coordination Digital Security Lab Ukraine, Defend Defenders, and Conexo, along with other partners around the globe, has developed a remote audit playlist, or collection of activities that can be performed remotely under varying conditions from low-bandwidth to distributed team scenarios. Some activities (such as reconnaissance) were already remote-friendly and do not require the auditor to be in-person. Other activities (such as device assessments) have been adapted to fit the remote context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;While the remote audit playlist includes a multitude of activities that can be done remotely, it is important to consider SAFETAG’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/blob/master/en/index.mva.md&quot;&gt;Minimal Viable Audit&lt;/a&gt;, designed as the starting point for an assessment to be considered viable under the SAFETAG framework.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial groundbreaking work to build a remote-friendly SAFETAG audit approach was first developed by the SAFETAG community during a &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/2017/08/31/Remote_Audits.html&quot;&gt;2017 content sprint&lt;/a&gt;. In 2020, however, remote-first audits have gone from being the exception to the rule, to driving the creation and refinement of approaches by Internews staff and partners in recent months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog highlights some considerations auditors should keep in mind when organizing and facilitating a remote audit. We’ve also highlighted below where to find existing content for your next virtual audit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;General considerations when conducting a remote audit&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare for the audit to take more time than normal.&lt;/strong&gt; When conducting remote audits, there are various factors to take into consideration in addition to those you would need to consider during in-person audits. A remote audit for example, almost certainly will &lt;strong&gt;require additional time&lt;/strong&gt; due to scheduling, coordination, and remote logistics management.  Be prepared for additional mishaps and factor in &lt;strong&gt;slow internet connections in any remote engagement.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare to be flexible.&lt;/strong&gt; Given we’re in the time of COVID, it is also wise to prepare to be flexible. Scheduling a team for a group exercise was difficult before the pandemic. Now it&apos;s even more challenging with alternate schedules and balancing life both in and outside of work. &lt;strong&gt;Think about smaller meetings and be intentional with who you invite.&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t require the entire organization if you don’t really need every single person at the organization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build trust as best you can.&lt;/strong&gt; This is an important factor to consider during remote audits, as your opportunity to ensure staff feel comfortable with you the auditor will be dependent on how you present yourself to them in a virtual setting. Remote meetings, particularly with individuals you are meeting for the first time, may require more effort to begin building that trust relationship with the individuals. Whereas in-person meetings allow for human connection and understanding through body language, &lt;strong&gt;remote meetings make nonverbal interactions more difficult.&lt;/strong&gt; As such, it is helpful to use &lt;strong&gt;video meetings whenever possible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is no perfect virtual replacement for in-person activities.&lt;/strong&gt; Auditors conducting a remote assessment must also accept this reality and be sure to communicate the limitations to the organization you are working with.  Remote audits have additional constraints and we must live within this reality for the moment or circumstance. A remote audit may require a combination of tactics and ultimately some compromises. When meeting in-person with an organization, it is easier to gain buy-in and encourage participation. If individuals are working remotely, it &lt;strong&gt;may be more difficult to maintain engagement.&lt;/strong&gt; Replacing a two-hour in-person meeting to map behaviors and workflows with a 50-question survey requesting the same information will likely not yield the same results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be prepared to not have all the information.&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes the very nature of the remote audit where you can’t check the office’s network or don’t have access to all the staff you need during the assessment process can leave you with information gaps that can be difficult to fill. Be creative in finding ways to connect the dots and look for the information as best you can.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider the size and structure of the organization.&lt;/strong&gt; A smaller organization, or one that is already remote, is easier to assess since staff members typically have a better internet connection and are more comfortable with virtual meetings. Large organizations who are used to working together in an office setting may have more challenges with remote working and may make it more difficult to assess virtually.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While remote audits require additional considerations and are not a perfect replacement for in-person audits, they can be done effectively. In upcoming posts we will provide a step-by-step guide for conducting remote assessments, as well as an introduction to the new SAFETAG web interface, which will allow users to customize a playlist based on the specific needs of the organization being audited.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SAFETAG Community Feedback]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is a cross-posted blog from Internews' USABLE.tools project which is advancing usable organizational security tools, including SAFETAG…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-09-24-CommunityFeedback</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-09-24-CommunityFeedback</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/CommunityFeedback.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image with title SAFETAG Community Feedback&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a cross-posted blog from Internews&apos; &lt;a href=&quot;https://USABLE.tools&quot;&gt;USABLE.tools&lt;/a&gt; project which is advancing usable organizational security tools, including SAFETAG. Read more about this effort on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://globaltech.internews.org/blog/introducing-adoptable&quot;&gt;Global Technology Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months, we have been working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tafka.mx&quot;&gt;Tafka&lt;/a&gt;, a Mexico-based design firm, to develop a new visual identity for the SAFETAG framework. As part of these efforts, we hosted 3 community feedback calls to gather feedback. Additionally, we shared an open survey for those who were unable to join the calls. In total, we received feedback from over 25 SAFETAG users around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have highlighted some of the feedback we received below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SAFETAG could be described as:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Complex, yet comprehensive”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Your really smart friend that you like a lot, but gives very detailed answers to very simple questions”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Flexible and adaptive”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What makes SAFETAG and its community unique?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We take the time to get to know, listen, and engage with the organization before starting hands-on work during the audit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are driven by the opportunity to support organizations advocating for civil and human rights, allowing them to do their work more safely and effectively&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We strive to provide holistic support to organizations, taking into consideration digital, physical, and psycho-social components of their security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We enable organizations to make informed decisions regarding their digital security, and contribute to building a more resilient and sustainable foundation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SAFETAG users believe the framework’s visual identity should be:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building blocks, or individual pieces that come together to form something larger and more comprehensive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colorful and approachable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Casual, yet professional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What challenges do users face when navigating the framework?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is big. As a new auditor, it is difficult to understand the “big picture”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The document is overwhelming, and it is hard to decide which parts are relevant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No clear hierarchy or organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The information architecture is not intuitive, and it is difficult to search for content that will be relevant for a specific organization, community, or context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What changes or features would make it easier to navigate?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to hide activities so that you can see a smaller version of the framework&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less words, more visuals. A clear naming structure and hierarchy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A search feature, and a way to select specific activities that are relevant for a particular scenario&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using metadata (such as size of organization, theme of activity, etc.) to sort the activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Videos, tutorials, and lessons learned for activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a clear “table of contents” so it is easy to locate a specific section or activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What challenges do users face when contributing new content to the framework?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many users do not feel comfortable contributing content through GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Others reported that contributing content currently takes too long; there are limited options for smaller, less time-consuming contributions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The process of contributing content is difficult&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to all who joined the feedback calls or responded to the survey! The insights you shared have directly informed the design and development of the new visual identity and web interface. We hope that the new visual assets and interface will make SAFETAG easier to use and more accessible for both new and experienced auditors. We are in the final stages of work and look forward to sharing the final products soon. Stay tuned for updates!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rights Con 2020: What happens between SAFETAG-based audits in NGOs? Long term tech support]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is a cross-posted blog from Internews' USABLE.tools project which is advancing usable organizational security tools, including SAFETAG…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-09-18-LongTermTech</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-09-18-LongTermTech</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/RC_01.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image with USABLE logo and title What happens between SAFETAG-based audits in NGOs? Long term tech support&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a cross-posted blog from Internews&apos; &lt;a href=&quot;https://USABLE.tools&quot;&gt;USABLE.tools&lt;/a&gt; project which is advancing usable organizational security tools, including SAFETAG. Read more about this effort on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://globaltech.internews.org/blog/introducing-adoptable&quot;&gt;Global Technology Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rightscon.org&quot;&gt;RightsCon&lt;/a&gt;, the world’s leading event on human rights in the digital age, was held online this year during the month of July 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dslua.org/&quot;&gt;Digital Security Lab Ukraine&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mdi.am/en/home/&quot;&gt;Media Diversity Institute Armenia&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://internews.org/&quot;&gt;Internews&lt;/a&gt; led a session entitled “What happens between SAFETAG-based audits and NGOs? Long-term tech support.” This session explored how audit findings and risk reduction plans can be converted into post-audit change; how long-term support and engagement with organizations can significantly boost both accuracy of security modeling and adoption of the best and context-relevant security practices; and the successes and failures they have experienced in practicing long-term organizational security. Lessons and best practices shared during the session can be found below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The panel was comprised of the following individuals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maksym Lunochkin, Security Auditor and Tech Support Specialist for Digital Security Lab Ukraine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anton Koushnir, Security Auditor and Trainer, Digital Security Lab Ukraine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vadym Gudyma, Security Auditor and Trainer, Digital Security Lab Ukraine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iryna Chulivska, Executive Director, Digital Security Lab Ukraine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mykola Kostynyan, Community Engagement Manager, Internews&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Artur Papyan, Director, Media Diversity Institute Armenia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is SAFETAG?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org&quot;&gt;SAFETAG&lt;/a&gt; is a professional audit framework that adapts traditional penetration testing and risk assessment methodologies to be relevant to smaller non-profit organizations based or operating in the developing world. SAFETAG audits serve small scale civil society organizations and independent media houses who have digital security concerns by working with them to identify the risks they face and providing capacity-aware, pragmatic next steps to address them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can your team prepare to provide long-term support?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All trainers and auditors have their own opinions on best practices, but it is critical to maintain humility and work with the organization to make sure that as an auditor, you are meeting them where they are and giving them what will be most useful for them - not what is most comfortable for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to prepare your team to provide support is to build a high-level checklist to think through prior to engagements. This checklist can include questions to consider prior to an audit, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many people will provide support?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who will coordinate the team and serve as the main point of contact for the organization?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will the team securely communicate with each other?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which organizations are we willing to support? Which are we not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time are we willing to dedicate to support?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will we measure the success of our support?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How and what will we document?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we as a team create interchangeable roles and back each other up?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What approaches should we consider when implementing long-term support?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to emphasize that organizations MUST own their own approach to risk and safety. As an auditor, you cannot push an organization to do one thing or another. You must explain, teach, support, and guide. Help implement as needed. If the organization cannot adopt and implement their own choices, their safety will not improve. If you are conducting an audit or monitoring incidents of digital security attacks, which are common against journalists and human rights defenders, your job is not only to respond to the attack - it is also to make sure the organization understands what has happened and what risks they are facing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also important to &lt;strong&gt;avoid fear mongering&lt;/strong&gt;. Too many digital security experts approach organizations by lecturing them on the risks they are facing and try to scare or pressure them into taking security measures. That is a really bad approach. Those facing risk are the best suited to understand it, navigate it, and mitigate it. You cannot force safety. You need to listen, provide guidance, and work with them to develop a plan and approach that makes sense for them. Threat models vary, and one is not like the other. Digital security is not a one size fits all approach, and one organization’s approach to safety will not be the same as the other. When providing support, your job is to make sure that both you and the organization have the information and support needed to make informed choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can we provide support remotely?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes, organizations’ websites are poorly maintained and no one within an organization takes on the role of maintaining security updates and recommendations. Through a project in Eastern Europe, Internews helps support the web development and digital security needs of media outlets and CSOs across the region. A particular dynamic of supporting websites is that, if an organization gives you login credentials, you can provide remote support.  This is different from providing infrastructural support to the organization, which may require physical access to servers, machines, etc. However, providing remote support also means that you must establish clear ethical lines - with credentials and remote access, you need to be very clear with the organization on roles and rules throughout the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How has Digital Security Lab Ukraine contextualized SAFETAG to the needs of their specific region?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAFETAG is an incredibly flexible framework and the similar technical infrastructure in many media outlets and CSOs means that some approaches to infrastructure can be streamlined. Additionally, DSLU pays a lot of attention to social media accounts and messaging apps, and often teaches on topics such as phishing because that is where they see a lot of risk being generated. They also focus on secure passwords, two-factor authentication (2fa), and developing best practices for how accounts are used. Additionally, DSLU hosts parties at their office to build community and will often join events where organizations who may need help will gather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does long-term support look like in practice?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When talking about long term support - it’s not three months; it’s not six months; it&apos;s not even a year. Long-term support requires years of commitment to support in auditing, providing guidance, and helping with necessary fixes. DSLU points out that while this requires an additional level of support and funding, it is important and effective when supporting organizations after an audit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The panelists shared the following tips for providing long-term support to organizations after they have received a SAFETAG security audit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consistent follow-up is key. Periodically ask how things are going in the organizations you support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build internal processes within your team in order to improve your own capacity to provide support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintain flexibility. In the long-term, organizations and people in them may change. Be flexible and willing to support them through those changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the process of getting, receiving, and finding help as simple and easy as possible for the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the beginning of the process, explain your role clearly and let the organization know what support you can offer now and in the long-term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[From Usability to Threat Modeling]]></title><description><![CDATA[What we have Our USABLE.tools project has a user persona library with 30+ user personas from around the world, representing LGBTQI activists…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-08-11-threatmodels</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-08-11-threatmodels</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/markus-winkler-aYPtEknQmXE-unsplash-blog.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stylized photo of puzzle pieces&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across our portfolio of technology, training, and advocacy to support a
free and open Internet that protects and advances human rights, we are
assembling a wide array of foundational resources (all released under
Creative Commons licenses!). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;boxtext&quot; style=&quot; width: 40%; float: right; padding-left: .5em; margin-left: 1em; border-left: 2px solid gray;&quot;&gt;
&lt;h5  style=&quot;font-size: .75em;&quot;&gt;Threat Modeling in Internet Freedom Projects&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;font-size: .75em; line-height:1em; text-align: justify; text-justify: inter-word;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;It&apos;s important to underline that this is not a new concept -- certainly
there are many security tools which already carefully consider threat
models during development; there is much written on using use cases and
&quot;misuse cases&quot; to expose the security and usability requirements for
tools -- this paper provides a good overview, and EFF&apos;s Security
Education Companion coverage of Threat Models introduces the concept for
use in training.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These include user personas with community-built lists of needs, and information about the threats or
adversaries they face. &lt;strong&gt;This collection of different resources is not
coincidental&lt;/strong&gt; – it builds a space in the middle to create detailed
&lt;strong&gt;threat models&lt;/strong&gt; around specific tools and practices and paves the way
to more expansive and cohesive long term digital safety strategies for
resilient communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What we have&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #005CAB;&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;At-Risk User Personas&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #FBB034;&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Contextual Digital Risk Assessments&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;padding: 15px;&quot; &gt;
&lt;!--&lt;img src=&quot;https://usable.tools//images/personas/ky-alexandria.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example persona face&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://USABLE.tools&quot;&gt;USABLE.tools&lt;/a&gt; project has a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://USABLE.tools/personas&quot;&gt;user persona library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; with 30+ user personas from around the world, representing LGBTQI activists, persons with disabilities, human rights defenders in closed states, and many more. These are not simply idealized stereotypes, however - they are created by the at-risk users themselves to provide authentic insight into the lived experiences, needs, and threats of these communities without putting any specific members of their community at risk. These personas provide critical insights into the needs and threats real people face in challenging environments. Tools for these communities need to be resilient against a wide variety of technical, physical, and legal attacks while also being easy to use, with little or no training.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--[**User Personas**](https://usable.tools/personas/), or anonymized profiles of end-users, provide a critical insight into the people who engage -- or whom developers want to engage -- with tools. When we are thinking about tools to protect marginalized persons, vulnerable populations, and/or the activists, advocates, and human rights defenders supporting them, the stakes are high. --&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;padding: 15px;&quot; &gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Risk Assessments&lt;/strong&gt; are a core of Internews&apos; internal risk management process, and we also strongly encourage auditors using the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://SAFETAG.org&quot;&gt;SAFETAG framework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to leverage a similar approach to research the technical and social context that they are working in when assessing an organization&apos;s security. The framework provides a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/tree/master/en/exercises/technical_context_research&quot;&gt;guide to research the technical capacity of potential threat actors&lt;/a&gt;, including both historical attack data and any indicators of changes to their capacity. Auditors are encouraged to also look at focal areas and trends.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What we&apos;re building&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://usable.tools/blog/2020-07-07-adoptable/&quot;&gt;next phase of USABLE&apos;s work&lt;/a&gt;, we will be building two new resources - &quot;personas&quot; which represent the needs of organizations and communities and “personas” which capture the capabilities and motivations of realistic but generalized adversaries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #6CB33F;&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Organizational Archetypes&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #F15D22;&quot;&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Adversary Personas&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;padding: 15px;&quot; &gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Organizational Archetypes capture the complex needs of organizations and communities, spanning from grassroots communities all the way up to donors in the space facing state-level adversaries.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are the more complex needs and different threats faced when collaborating? Secure messaging, calls, and document collaboration are all significantly more complex when you have multiple people or organizations involved, and tools which are relatively easy to swap in and out at a personal level become incredibly more complex if an entire organization depends upon them as a core part of their workflow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;padding: 15px;&quot; &gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adversary Personas will contain realistic details of generalized adversaries’ capacities and what issues these actors are willing to expend resources and build capacity to undermine.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Organizations will be able to use these resources to anticipate potential threats and malicious actions and proactively develop practices and responses to realistic situations. This will enable developers, trainers, policymakers, funders, and others to contextualize their work against a wider variety of threat actors without having to rely on any one specific nation-state as a &quot;bogeyman.&quot; I specifically hope this enables richer conversation around actual threats while removing cultural stereotypes and prejudices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;From Resources to Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are collectively designed to enable unbiased discussions and
strategy development around the serious challenges and threats users,
organizations, and entire communities face, the tools we use to help,
and tools, practices, or policies we wish we had.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responses focused on threats, not just threat actors&lt;/strong&gt; Threat
actors change and evolve, and often have more capacity than is
publicly confirmed (but perhaps less than is presumed through
rumor). By extracting and de-personalizing aspects of this, we can
have clearer discussions. Further, specifying current existing
actors, especially in open source tools, can overly complicate the
public profile of the tool as well as those using it. If a tool is
clearly built to combat a specific actor, then users of that tool
can be seen as inherently being aligned against that actor. This has
resulted already in excessive targeting and jailing of activists
based on their tool choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identification of common, cross-regional threats&lt;/strong&gt; What attacks,
specific techniques, and even malicious tools are being used and
re-used globally? Are there patterns we can detect and build
proactive defenses against?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gap identification&lt;/strong&gt; What gaps remain when we look at this data
mapped out? Is anyone working to address them? What solutions
(tools, training, policy changes) could be used? How do we
sustainably build these resources?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More dynamic responses, more resilient communities&lt;/strong&gt; By tackling
the inputs into this process separately, we can update our models
more agilely and plan against a wider variety of attacks to build
tools and guidance that are more resilient to more types of threat
actors as well as changes in any specific actor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future-looking strategies&lt;/strong&gt; With these fictional personas and
archetypes, we do not have to be as limited to current actors and
their capacities. We can (within reason) consider possible future
threats that activists may face by remixing and extrapolating from
current threats. Anticipating these risks will allow us to build
tools to mitigate sooner, rather than later. &lt;em&gt;Dystopian cyberpunk
scenarios welcome!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These resources can be used to develop &lt;strong&gt;tabletop scenarios&lt;/strong&gt; to
explore current and emerging threats and build creative responses to
them. These scenarios are useful in advanced trainings, tool
development, and strategy building exercises. Fictional but
realistic adversaries and personas can get into detail around
specific threats and mitigations without being as personal, risking
bias, and helping reduce potential of trauma involved in these
discussions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are just getting started and would love to hear from you on what
data you hope to find in these resources, how you would use and adapt
them, and more! You can reach us at
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:connect@usable.tools&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;connect@usable.tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Introducing ADOPTABLE]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is a cross-posted blog from Internews' USABLE.tools project which is advancing usable organizational security tools, including SAFETAG…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-07-06-adoptable</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-07-06-adoptable</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a cross-posted blog from Internews&apos; &lt;a href=&quot;https://USABLE.tools&quot;&gt;USABLE.tools&lt;/a&gt; project which is advancing usable organizational security tools, including SAFETAG. Read more about this effort on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://globaltech.internews.org/blog/introducing-adoptable&quot;&gt;Global Technology Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Equipping at-risk organizations with localized expertise, resources, and tools to mitigate digital attacks&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human rights organizations around the globe continue to face ongoing and increasing digital security threats from state and non-state actors. ADOPTABLE (Adaptable Digital and Organizational Protections by Transforming and Building Long-term Ecosystems) is an Internews project designed to help these at-risk organizations access relevant resources (human, financial, and technical tools) that will allow them to continue to operate safely. Without access to local organizational security experts, usable security and privacy tools, buy-in from decision-makers, and support from funders to adopt stronger safety practices, the organizations and their beneficiaries remain at risk, as does their crucial work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The project consists of four core components:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Expanding the capacity of regional and local partners to address organizational security risks&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Internews will support experienced partners in Latin America, Sub-Saharan Africa, and Eastern Europe to become &lt;strong&gt;regionally recognized centers of expertise&lt;/strong&gt; on organizational security and build out local and regional ecosystems of organizational security auditors. Partners will conduct Trainings of Auditors (ToA’s) to train and/or upskill local security auditors in their regions on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SAFETAG framework&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. These newly trained auditors will work with experienced auditors to gain first-hand experience in conducting audits, while also collecting feedback on organizational security tools being used by at-risk organizations. To improve the scalability of this localization of expertise, Internews is also working to improve the SAFETAG onboarding and training process and make the framework more accessible by developing a &lt;strong&gt;new interface&lt;/strong&gt;. More on that process &lt;a href=&quot;https://usable.tools/blog/2020-05-13-safetag-community-call/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Improving the adoption of organizational security practices within at-risk organizations&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Internews will fund at least 5 audits or engagements in each of the three target regions. At-risk organizations will undergo a &lt;strong&gt;full security audit&lt;/strong&gt; and receive a detailed &lt;strong&gt;Risk Reduction Plan&lt;/strong&gt; (RRP), which outlines tangible steps they can take to mitigate their risks. Even after a security audit, Internews has found that many organizations lack the resources needed to implement the recommendations provided by an expert. Without the ability to implement these changes, organizations are no more secure than they were before an audit. Internews will ensure that these organizations are able to implement the recommended changes by &lt;strong&gt;providing direct financial support after the audits&lt;/strong&gt;. A variety of mitigation efforts may be eligible for support, including trainings for organization staff, facilitation of a security service by a third party, or the purchase of software and hardware.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Developing and enhancing feedback collection mechanisms to ensure at-risk users have a voice in the design and development of open source privacy and security tools&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the USABLE approach, Internews created feedback loops between at-risk users, digital security trainers, and open source tool developers. Internews will continue to collect feedback from at-risk individual users, while also expanding to capture organization-wide feedback on security and privacy tools. Most notably, the USABLE approach will be integrated into the SAFETAG framework, allowing SAFETAG auditors to identify gaps and usability issues with privacy tools being used at the organizational level. Through virtual &lt;a href=&quot;https://usable.tools/blog/2020-04-03-cross-regional-convenings/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-Regional Convenings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Internews will work with partners to update the activities in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://usable.tools/guidebook&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UX Feedback Collection Guidebook&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;/a&gt; develop organizational archetypes to further build out our library of user personas, and map the current landscape of open source tools being used by at-risk communities around the globe. Following the virtual convenings, Internews will launch a &lt;strong&gt;pool of funding for trainers and auditors&lt;/strong&gt; to integrate feedback collection activities into their digital security trainings or organizational audits. The high-quality feedback collected during these engagements will be shared with developers through their preferred channels. Key communities will convene once more at the end of the project for the third &lt;strong&gt;UXForum&lt;/strong&gt; to continue devising ways to scale and sustain feedback loops.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Enhancing the usability and accessibility of open source privacy and security tools&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Internews will launch the third round of the &lt;strong&gt;UX Fund&lt;/strong&gt;. This funding pool will provide support to privacy and security tool teams, enabling them to work with UX and accessibility experts to implement human-centered, usability-focused tool improvements. These changes will ultimately strengthen the tools, making them more &lt;strong&gt;secure for the at-risk individuals and organizations&lt;/strong&gt; who need them the most.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, &lt;strong&gt;we believe that with more localized tools and stronger local support, at-risk organizations will be better equipped to withstand the digital attacks and surveillance they currently face.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[IFF Organizational Security Village Day 4]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-11-virtual-orgsec-village-day4</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-11-virtual-orgsec-village-day4</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event is bringing together security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners for a five-day program of over 20 community-led sessions exploring five major themes in organizational security.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions on Day 4 focused on responding to advanced threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Highlights from Day 4 of the OrgSec village included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A conversation on &lt;strong&gt;community insights to improve automated threat modeling&lt;/strong&gt;, gathering inputs from a diverse range of individuals and groups regarding the threats they face.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session demonstrating how to &lt;strong&gt;build a threat lab with your bare hands … and a laptop.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An overview of &lt;strong&gt;digital threat information sharing for human rights&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Key takeaways from the discussions included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threat detection isn’t only about fancy technology!&lt;/strong&gt; A lot of endpoint detection is process and practice-oriented. Impressing the importance of antivirus and software updates, teaching partners what abnormal activity looks like, or making sure they know the process for calling first responders takes training, process development, and awareness raising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust is a key component of threat information sharing.&lt;/strong&gt; Knowing who and where to share information about threats requires personal connections and existing trust relationships, which can feel like a barrier to entering the space. But community networks like the Computer Incident Response Center for Civil Society (CiviCERT) and information sharing standards such as the Traffic Light Protocol (TLP) can lower barriers and facilitate sharing through established community standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting started in threat analysis requires trust, skills, and time.&lt;/strong&gt; Though you will eventually need computers powerful enough to run virtual machines, more advanced skills, and connections to other researchers and communities like CiviCERT, don’t be intimidated by the technical jargon! All it takes to get started is a willingness to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Human rights advocates are facing attacks&lt;/strong&gt; such as phishing and publication of their identifying details by government or state-sponsored adversaries that are based on online open source intelligence (OSINT) gathering. When threat modeling, it is important to identify the types of public data that makes you vulnerable and that adversaries may try to exploit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Join us for the last day!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join us for the final sessions this Friday, with a focus on on assessing impact and funding organizational security!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Register at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/IFFOSV_Title.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Five OrgSec Village Themes are 1. Approaches to OrgSec 2. OrgSec In Practice 3. Advanced Threats 4. Funding OrgSec Work 5. Monitoring and Evaluation&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[IFF Organizational Security Village Day 5]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-12-virtual-orgsec-village-day5</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-12-virtual-orgsec-village-day5</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event is bringing together security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners for a five-day program of over 20 community-led sessions exploring five major themes in organizational security.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions on Day 5 focused on funding OrgSec work and Monitoring &amp;#x26; Evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Highlights from Day 5 of the OrgSec village included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A discussion around how small, local digital support initiatives can &lt;strong&gt;fund digital security assistance&lt;/strong&gt; for nonprofits through strategic networking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A brainstorm around ways to better &lt;strong&gt;support digital security programs&lt;/strong&gt; through informing and coordinating with donors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An open dialogue on &lt;strong&gt;evaluating audit success&lt;/strong&gt; from an auditor’s perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A presentation of frameworks to measure the &lt;strong&gt;impact of organizational security work&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Key takeaways from the discussions included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Securing funding is a challenge for OrgSec practitioners.&lt;/strong&gt; Organizations need to better incorporate digital and organizational security into their budgets and marketing and communications plans. More broadly, there is a need for coordination within the local and international OrgSec community to promote knowledge sharing and establish partnerships in order to educate and coordinate with donors more effectively. Donors also need to adopt digital security practices that allow them to engage with organizations and support their work safely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community members debated the value of establishing certifications or skills qualifications&lt;/strong&gt; for work in the space in order to reduce the reliance on trust networks. This could reduce barriers to funding and opportunities for work for new practitioners who may be less known to both funders and at-risk organizations seeking support. However, establishing community-wide agreed upon standards and mitigating the substantial additional barriers to entry (e.g. cost, training opportunities and locations, personal and unfunded time) caused by any such certification system pose a formidable challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measuring the impact of OrgSec programs is important&lt;/strong&gt; in order to evaluate and improve approaches and communicate success to donors. While it is easy to focus on measuring purely digital risk, is it important to bear in mind that effective OrgSec should take a holistic approach also incorporating psychosocial support and physical aspects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Whether to evaluate OrgSec interventions using shared community standards or by measuring change within an organization and against its own threat model&lt;/strong&gt; continued to inspire debate among community members. The Engine Room shared a Monitoring and Evaluation Framework for Organisational Security - which takes the latter approach - for practitioners to adapt for their own M&amp;#x26;E practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you for participating in OrgSec this week! If you’d like to continue the conversation head to &lt;a href=&quot;https://orgsec.community/display/OS&quot;&gt;https://orgsec.community/display/OS&lt;/a&gt;. We will be posting shared notes from the event on the wiki next week!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/IFFOSV_Title.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Five OrgSec Village Themes are 1. Approaches to OrgSec 2. OrgSec In Practice 3. Advanced Threats 4. Funding OrgSec Work 5. Monitoring and Evaluation&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[IFF Organizational Security Village Day 3]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-11-virtual-orgsec-village-day3</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-11-virtual-orgsec-village-day3</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event is bringing together security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners for a five-day program of over 20 community-led sessions exploring five major themes in organizational security.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions on Day 3 continued to explore examples of OrgSec in Practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Highlights from Day 3 of the OrgSec village included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A collective discussion around what we mean as a community when we say &lt;strong&gt;OrgSec Crisis Response&lt;/strong&gt;, and how we can provide comprehensive crisis response support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An informal session sharing practitioners’ experiences conducting &lt;strong&gt;Remote Organizational Assessments, Remote Tech Assistance, and other remote interventions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A case study of one organization’s experience launching a &lt;strong&gt;Website with Digital Security Instructions&lt;/strong&gt; and the unexpected ways audiences used it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A presentation on the &lt;strong&gt;RAWRR (Risk Assessment Workflow Recommendation Roadmap)&lt;/strong&gt; tool for documenting security assessments,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;risk modelling, recommendation development and implementation monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A review of &lt;strong&gt;Security Governance in CSOs&lt;/strong&gt; exploring ways to scale policy development approaches to different sizes, capacities, and complexities of organisations and communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Key takeaways from the discussions included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remote interventions do work, but require more time and preparation than face-to-face support.&lt;/strong&gt;  Remote interventions can save time and money spent on travel, and can be the right format for rapid response or consultations (especially when trust is already established) as well as for facilitated online learning. However, they require significant time investment, and present numerous additional challenges. For example, remote trust building is tricky, and many people are uncomfortable enabling remote device access. Technical barriers like poor internet connectivity or lack of tech skills among staff may emerge. Finally, it is impossible to provide full technical support if something goes wrong that can&apos;t be fixed remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web-based digital security guides are not dead (but keep them simple)!&lt;/strong&gt; Websites with complicated interactive guides addressing specific threat models don’t get sustained engagement and are difficult and expensive to maintain long-term. In contrast, sites with a set of searchable, specific, and updated instructions for different tools and cases can be a useful resource for post-audit and training communications and remote support and incident response. In addition, they are easier to keep up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s crucial to tailor security audit reports to the audience in mind.&lt;/strong&gt; Whether the report is for management or IT staff with technical know-how will dictate the specificity and structure of the report. There was community consensus that risk should be the focus of audit reports. Shorter reports focusing on action steps may be useful for organizations with limited bandwidth and interest in holistic security; in-depth reports detailing the process and connecting recommendations to risk are a more useful resource for organizations wishing to replicate the process down the line or build their own internal digital security expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When developing organizational security policies, don’t start from scratch!&lt;/strong&gt; There are many existing policy frameworks for practitioners to draw upon when assisting civil society organizations. Start with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usesoap.app&quot;&gt;SOAP&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sdamanual.org/&quot;&gt;SDA&lt;/a&gt;, and resources from &lt;a href=&quot;https://communitydocs.accessnow.org/370-Organizational_Security_Policy.html&quot;&gt;Access Now&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://orgsec.community/display/OS/Creating+organisational+security+policies&quot;&gt;OrgSec Wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;It’s not too late to register!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join us for more sessions throughout the week on OrgSec in Practice, Advanced Threats, Funding Models, and more!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Register at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/IFFOSV_Title.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Five OrgSec Village Themes are 1. Approaches to OrgSec 2. OrgSec In Practice 3. Advanced Threats 4. Funding OrgSec Work 5. Monitoring and Evaluation&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[IFF Organizational Security Village Day 2]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-10-virtual-orgsec-village-day2</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-10-virtual-orgsec-village-day2</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event is bringing together security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners for a five-day program of over 20 community-led sessions exploring five major themes in organizational security.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions on Day 2 explored examples of OrgSec in Practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Highlights from Day 2 of the OrgSec village included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A collaborative survey of the &lt;strong&gt;OrgSec Community’s Response to Emerging Crises&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A presentation of work carried out with the &lt;strong&gt;Mechanism for the Integral Protection of Human Rights Defenders and Journalists in Mexico City&lt;/strong&gt;, including a typology and workflow for the diagnosis of digital incidents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A discussion around &lt;strong&gt;Non-technical Due Diligence when choosing security tools and services&lt;/strong&gt;, exploring questions on jurisdiction, open sourcing, and reputation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An exploration of alliances as a support mechanism to guarantee the &lt;strong&gt;Digital Security of Human Rights Defenders Working in Civic and Internet Repressive Environments&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A step-by-step playbook of the &lt;strong&gt;OrgSec Audit Process&lt;/strong&gt; in different contexts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A hard look at how &lt;strong&gt;Digital Security Trainings can do More Harm than Good&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Key takeaways from the discussions included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-sector partnerships can expand OrgSec support.&lt;/strong&gt; At times, it can be advantageous for organizations providing digital security support to at-risk communities to coordinate with government agencies offering similar support mechanisms. Traditional training methods combined with local and federal protection mechanisms allow for maximum protection for those communities who are most at-risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approaches to OrgSec must be adapted to the local context or threat model.&lt;/strong&gt; What may be a serious threat to one organization, may not be to another. When working with an organization, it is important to understand the threats that are relative to their work and/or location. What are the risks that they face? What has been happening to similar organizations in the region? It is not a one-size-fits-all approach, but rather needs to be tailored to the needs and capacity of each organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empower organizations with the knowledge and guidance to understand and mitigate their risks.&lt;/strong&gt; Security can be overwhelming, particularly for less-technical users. It is critical for an auditor or trainer to focus on the how and why and not just the end result. The more organizations understand, the more confident they will be. This will better equip them to replicate the process in the future. Accessible language and easy to navigate guides and checklists can facilitate this sharing of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know when your support does more harm than good.&lt;/strong&gt; Digital security trainings are helpful -- except for when they’re not. As an auditor or trainer, it is often difficult to find the time needed to properly onboard organizations to the security practices they need. Behavior change takes time and cannot be accomplished in a two-hour training session. There is no guarantee that the organization will continue to properly use (or use at all) a tool or software installed or downloaded during the training. OrgSec practitioners must be aware of these limitations, as insufficient training or support may lead to a false sense of security and can ultimately put the organization at a greater risk than they were to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SAFETAG is meant to be a general framework.&lt;/strong&gt; The SAFETAG framework serves as a toolbox, or collection of relevant tools and activities that can be used to conduct an organizational security audit. When planning for an audit, the auditor must select which tools and activities are most relevant based on the local context, size of the organization, and resources available. Some activities may be too complicated or irrelevant. You do not need to complete every activity in the SAFETAG framework!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;It’s not too late to register!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join us for more sessions throughout the week on OrgSec in Practice, Advanced Threats, Funding Models, and more!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Register at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/IFFOSV_Title.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Five OrgSec Village Themes are 1. Approaches to OrgSec 2. OrgSec In Practice 3. Advanced Threats 4. Funding OrgSec Work 5. Monitoring and Evaluation&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[IFF Organizational Security Village Day 1]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-09-virtual-orgsec-village-day1</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-06-09-virtual-orgsec-village-day1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Internews is hosting the virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational Security Village throughout this week (June 8-12)! The event is bringing together security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners for a five-day program of over 20 community-led sessions exploring five major themes in organizational security.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sessions on Day 1 centered around diverse approaches to OrgSec adopted by practitioners in the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Highlights from Day 1 of the OrgSec village included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A co-creation session on making Organizational Security Community Spaces more Useful, Inclusive, and Resilient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A discussion on ways to Scale Organizational Security Assistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session on Strategies to Avoid Dependency and Deliver Lasting Change through OrgSec interventions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A conversation around the Importance of Long Term Support and Engagement beyond digital security assessments in delivering organizational change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Key takeaways from the discussions included:&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The goal of OrgSec work is to make itself obsolete!&lt;/strong&gt; While it is easy to focus on tangible outputs like audits or reports, most auditors and trainers prioritize increased internal organizational security expertise and decreased dependence on external security help. Effective strategies include finding digital security champions within organizations and building capacity in the surrounding community. Building the confidence and ability of those in the organizations to put digital security into practice is just as important as hardening their digital security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organizational Security assistance is not being made available to those who need it the most.&lt;/strong&gt; In the US and globally marginalized communities facing the greatest threats are also those with least access to critical digital security resources (both human and financial). It is imperative to address this fact when designing programs and change the language we are using to be more inclusive of these communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A security audit or assessment is just the beginning!&lt;/strong&gt; Most organizations need long-term support to make an effective change in their practices and harden their defenses against digital security attacks. Despite this, funding structures supporting current OrgSec work are not conducive to long-term engagement. Practitioners need to consider how to bake sustainability and long-term support into program design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;It’s not too late to register!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join us for more sessions throughout the week on OrgSec in Practice, Advanced Threats, Funding Models, and more!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Register at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/IFFOSV_Title.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Five OrgSec Village Themes are 1. Approaches to OrgSec 2. OrgSec In Practice 3. Advanced Threats 4. Funding OrgSec Work 5. Monitoring and Evaluation&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Join us for the IFF Organizational Security Village!]]></title><description><![CDATA[IFF OrgSec Village Internews is excited to announce that we will be hosting a virtual Internet Freedom Festival (IFF) Organizational…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-05-26-virtual-orgsec-village</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-05-26-virtual-orgsec-village</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/IFFOSV_Title.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Five OrgSec Village Themes are 1. Approaches to OrgSec 2. OrgSec In Practice 3. Advanced Threats 4. Funding OrgSec Work 5. Monitoring and Evaluation&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; padding: 1em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;IFF OrgSec Village&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Internews is excited to announce that we will be hosting a virtual &lt;a href=&quot;https://internetfreedomfestival.org/&quot;&gt;Internet Freedom Festival (IFF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Organizational Security Village&lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;June 8-12&lt;/strong&gt;. This event will bring together security auditors, digital security trainers, and other experts and practitioners for a five-day program of over 20 community-led sessions exploring five major themes in organizational security.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center &quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/IFFOSV_Theme.png&quot; alt=&quot;Five OrgSec Village Themes are 1. Approaches to OrgSec 2. OrgSec In Practice 3. Advanced Threats 4. Funding OrgSec Work 5. Monitoring and Evaluation&quot; style=&quot;border: 0; width: 75%; padding: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Virtual Village Format&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on feedback from the community, we have decided to host live sessions during the week, with each day of programming beginning around 12:30 UTC, and ending no later than 20:00 UTC. Each session will last approximately 50 minutes, with a short break in between sessions. We will be sharing a schedule and additional information on each session prior to the event. You are invited to join as many or as few sessions as you would like!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recognize that some folks may not be able to join due to timing or prior engagements. To ensure that everyone has the opportunity to contribute in some way, non-attributed, editable notes from each session will be made available. We will also use the IFF Mattermost for asynchronous collaboration and networking. &lt;strong&gt;If you do not have an IFF Mattermost account, please email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:team@internetfreedomfestival.org&quot;&gt;team@internetfreedomfestival.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Registration and CoC&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please let us know you will be attending by registering here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd_vzeIABKyYt1pMiq4_Ka-Ffk8kcjGmHnJQw9-n2UCfjAbig/viewform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We ask that you register even if you are only able to attend a few days or sessions. Event access details will only be shared with registered participants. Please also complete the registration form if you are not able to join the live sessions but would like to review notes or contribute asynchronously.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This event will follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.internetfreedomfestival.org/wiki/index.php/Code_of_Conduct&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;IFF Code of Conduct&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Community Call for Feedback!!]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last month, we shared that we would be updating the visual identity of SAFETAG, including the development of a new logo, color-scheme, and…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-03-15-SAFETAGdesign</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-03-15-SAFETAGdesign</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last month, we shared that we would be updating the visual identity of SAFETAG, including the development of a new logo, color-scheme, and iconography. We are excited to share that we  will be working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://showcase.dropbox.com/s/This-is-tafka-MX9NBtr2zTzngWhO2EVLp&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tafka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a design collective based in Mexico, and are officially starting the re-design process!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Why re-design SAFETAG?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have decided to re-design SAFETAG to provide a more cohesive and recognizable brand. The new digital assets will be used across the website, interface (more details below), and all other SAFETAG documentation. Our hope is that this new design will make content more accessible for users, particularly new auditors that may have previously struggled with navigating through the framework.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;New Interface (coming soon)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the re-design, we are working with a development team to build a new SAFETAG interface that is easier to use and more accessible for both new and experienced auditors. The new interface will allow auditors to generate “playlists,” or collections of audit activities, tailored to a specific type of organization or risk environment. These customized and shareable playlists can be stored for future reference or shared with other auditors working in similar contexts. We are expecting to launch the new interface during the late summer or early fall of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;We need you!&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to make sure that the new design reflects the needs of the SAFETAG community, we would like to invite all SAFETAG users, both new and experienced, to share feedback with us. We will be holding &lt;strong&gt;two open community calls&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;strong&gt;May 19, 2020 at 10:30 am ET and another on May 21 at 9:00 am ET.&lt;/strong&gt; Please let us know you will be attending one of the calls by registering &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdbcQm-IR0tUdC32T1dzRNxgEa_oAfMk9gNlcyNvkoTHgsTRw/viewform&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We will be sharing details for joining the call directly via email with those who RSVP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the community feedback calls, we would also like to invite community members to complete a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSe_4r7JM8YDEj17h-IgPgXOM0PS2BGyMek1JLyW0wKHyBkAFQ/viewform&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;short survey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; This 20-question survey will allow us to collect any ideas and feedback you may have and provide space for those who may not be able to join one of the community feedback calls to share thoughts asynchronously. We look forward to hearing from you and incorporating your thoughts and feedback into this design process!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Re-designing SAFETAG: Developing a Brand]]></title><description><![CDATA[We are currently looking for a designer to help us develop a new, updated brand for our SAFETAG methodology. SAFETAG is an auditing…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-03-09-call-design</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-03-09-call-design</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 01:01:01 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;We are currently looking for a designer to help us develop a new, updated brand for our SAFETAG methodology. SAFETAG is an auditing framework, created to work with small-scale media houses and civil society organizations who have digital security concerns by identifying the risks they face and providing capacity-aware, pragmatic next steps to address them. Ultimately, SAFETAG was created to make these small organizations stronger and more resilient to the threats they are up against.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are in the process of developing a new interface for the SAFETAG framework, which will be interactive and easier for users (both new and experienced) to navigate. The interface will allow users to create their own playlists comprised of the SAFETAG activities they will be using during an audit. In advance of the launch of this new interface, we are hoping to bring a fresh new face to the SAFETAG methodology, including a new logo. The new brand and imaging will be used across the website, interface, and all other SAFETAG documentation. Our goal is to establish a relevant brand that is both informative and accessible for all who engage with the SAFETAG framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We expect this design process to take a total of 4-6 weeks, including time for interviews with our more experienced SAFETAG partners and the Internews team. See below for an expected timeline and outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Organizations, companies, or individuals are eligible to apply for this opportunity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/aBcZ6mJf2CuJx22m7&quot;&gt;Please apply using this form&lt;/a&gt; if this is an opportunity you are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Expected Timeline (may be adjusted)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weeks 1-2:&lt;/strong&gt; Review of SAFETAG framework, including interviews with 4-6 key community leads. Internews will organize at least two community calls for partners or community leads to provide insight and feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weeks 2-3:&lt;/strong&gt; Present 3-5 concepts with explanation describing how community feedback was used to inform the design process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weeks 3-4:&lt;/strong&gt; Refine and finalize selected concept.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weeks 4-6:&lt;/strong&gt; Implement the concept in the below outputs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Requested Outputs&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visual identity / brand development for the SAFETAG framework&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logo for SAFETAG, with the following alternative appearances:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Square for website favicons / &quot;user&quot; icons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black/White only&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reversed-out versions for dark and light backgrounds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Style guide that can be used for both print documents and websites, to include:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Selection of open-licensed fonts for headers and normal text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creation of a  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG21/&quot;&gt;web content accessibility guidelines AA/AAA &lt;/a&gt; compliant color palette&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text/visual element styling (headers, buttons in active/inactive states, call-out textboxes, unordered bulleted list items, checklists, hyperlink formatting, footnote/reference formatting)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific visual iconography to support SAFETAG&apos;s content and structure (e.g. different icons for technical, research, and interactive elements of the framework which align with the overall branding, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/2018/08/16/SAFETAGStories-dropbox.html&quot;&gt;our &quot;TRI&quot; approach&lt;/a&gt; for background)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All inputs and outputs should be compatible with a CC-BY-SA 4.0 license&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Shape the agenda for the Internet Freedom Festival's OrgSec Village]]></title><description><![CDATA[UPDATE: IFF has been cancelled! Please read the official statement at the IFF website We are reviewing the OrgSec Village applications and…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2020-01-27-OrgSecVillage</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2020-01-27-OrgSecVillage</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;UPDATE: IFF has been cancelled!&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://internetfreedomfestival.org/wiki/index.php/Cancellation_of_the_2020_Internet_Freedom_Festival&quot;&gt;official statement at the IFF website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We are reviewing the OrgSec Village applications and considering options to revisit this through other conferences later in 2020 or virtually.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internews will be the host of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://internetfreedomfestival.org/&quot;&gt;Internet Freedom Festival&lt;/a&gt;&apos;s first-ever Organizational Security Village - &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/AiLgB9PHdq3ka3Tt9&quot;&gt;Propose your session today&lt;/a&gt; !&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://internetfreedomfestival.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://internetfreedomfestival.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/Captura-de-pantalla-2019-06-19-a-las-15.54.19.png&quot; alt=&quot;Internet Freedom Festival: Save the Date - April 20-24&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This two-day event will bring together digital security trainers, security auditors, and other experts and practitioners for lightning talks, interactive workshops, collaborative discussions, and relevant hands-on labs and skill-shares.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Shape the agenda&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To ensure that the content covered during the village reflects the needs of the community, we are inviting you to help us shape the agenda.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please complete &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/AiLgB9PHdq3ka3Tt9&quot;&gt;this short application&lt;/a&gt; to propose sessions&lt;/strong&gt; or topics that you would like to explore further. Deadline for submission is &lt;strong&gt;February 28, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;. All selected submissions will be notified by March 20, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are few ideas for discussion that we&apos;ve already heard and would welcome specific conversations around, but please do not feel limited to just this list:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Threat-sharing across communities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving diversity in OrgSec work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens after SAFETAG? What does long-term engagement with organizations look like? How are others building reports and Risk Reduction Plans?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is doing what, conversations, Q&amp;#x26;A sessions etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presenting / sharing working materials, anonymized reports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conducting a remote audit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dealing with more advanced threats &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measuring audit’s success, how do we know we did a good job?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving and expanding the SAFETAG framework + interface &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;We look forward to seeing you there!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Curricula updates and new approaches for emerging challenges!]]></title><description><![CDATA[Curricula Updates  The SAFETAG Curriculum has also been updated to better match the changes to the SAFETAG methodology over the past 2 years…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2019-02-25-Emerging_Challenges</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2019-02-25-Emerging_Challenges</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2019 13:49:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Curricula Updates&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://karisma.org.co/nueva-guia-para-auditorias-en-seguridad-digital&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/karisma-curriculo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Karisma&apos;s  SAFETAG Curriculum&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; style=&quot;float: right; width: 40%;&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SAFETAG Curriculum has also been updated to better match the changes to the SAFETAG methodology over the past 2 years and introduce some of the clarifying context (such as the TRI approach) to selecting activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on their work training auditors in Colombia, &lt;a href=&quot;https://karisma.org.co&quot;&gt;Fundación Karisma&lt;/a&gt; developed a custom curriculum (in Spanish) that adapts the SAFETAG methodology to reflect the needs and context of Colombian civil society organizations. It is included as part of the 0.7.0 release and available directly from Karisma: &lt;a href=&quot;https://karisma.org.co/nueva-guia-para-auditorias-en-seguridad-digital&quot;&gt;Currículo para auditores de seguridad digital&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Emerging Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;SAFETAG Fellows and partners gathered for a 3-day workshop in September 2018 to expand the guidance that the SAFETAG framework has for auditors to assist organizations facing emerging challenges and new technology such as increased reliance on cloud services, the Internet of Things, and more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition; &lt;a href=&quot;https://accessnow.org&quot;&gt;AccessNow&lt;/a&gt; developed two new activities from their work with vulnerable populations which help capture the personal aspects of organizational security.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all the contributions and support from the fellows in creating this!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This updated content is available in the repository and as pre-compiled PDFs in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/releases/tag/0.7.0&quot;&gt;0.7 release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;New Method and Activities for reviewing organizational policies&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;While implicit across multiple parts of SAFETAG, this new method formalizes a review process for reviewing both formal and informal policies and practices of organizations; leveraging inputs from the Capacity Assessment methodology and adding two specific exercises, one for working with organizations with formal policies and one for identifying informal agreements and practices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;New and Updated Activities&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h5&gt;&quot;Night in the Life&quot;&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;p&gt;This activity has the auditor discuss with the staff about their practices, personal devices, software and other security capabilities that they use outside of work. This is used to develop a report component exposing how practices outside of their work can affect their personal security and that of the organization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Self Doxing&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doxing (also &quot;doxxing&quot;, or &quot;d0xing&quot;, a word derived from &quot;documents&quot;, or &quot;docs&quot;) consists in tracing and gathering information about someone using sources that are freely available on the internet (called OSINT, or Open Source INTelligence).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doxing is premised on the idea that &quot;The more you know about your target, the easier it will be to find their flaws”. A malicious actor may use this method to identify valuable information about their target. Once they have found sensitive information, they may publish this information for defamation, blackmail the target person, or use it for other goals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This activity aims to help participants identify any unwanted personal information that may be publicly available online, and to make them aware of the risk of doxing and how to prevent it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Cloud Provider Assessment&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is increasingly difficult to run complex organizations without some reliance on cloud-based service providers such as email hosting, web hosting, or document management/backup. Organizations (and as assisted by the auditor) should review their options in the selection of cloud providers, and in parallel consider ways to apply practices and policies to their use to meet organizational security requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This activity helps auditors both enumerate the cloud providers the organization works with (formally/officially and as shadow IT infrastructure), map out what data and metadata is shared where, what access and technical controls are available, and assess risks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Updates to Network Scanning: Assessing IoT devices&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have significantly updated and streamlined the network scanning activity to include overall guidelines for identifying and assessing IoT devices on office networks. In addition, it&apos;s worth highlighting an entire activity devoted to working with VOIP systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Work still in draft&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also began a section called &quot;Fear Mapping&quot; to help identify, quantify, and manage fears. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/issues/397&quot;&gt;issue #397&lt;/a&gt; for the status and next steps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Translations of SAFETAG]]></title><description><![CDATA[SAFETAG's Information flow in Arabic We are happy to announce that SAFETAG's methods are now available in Russian, Arabic, and Spanish…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2019-02-22-Translations</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2019-02-22-Translations</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 12:49:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/ar-flow.png&quot; alt=&quot;SAFETAG&amp;#x27;s Information flow in Arabic&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce that SAFETAG&apos;s methods are now available in Russian, Arabic, and Spanish (updated)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/releases/download/0.6.0/Arabic.pdf&quot;&gt;العربية&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/releases/download/0.6.0/English.pdf&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/releases/download/0.6.0/Spanish.pdf&quot;&gt;Español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/releases/download/0.6.0/Russian.pdf&quot;&gt;русский&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please give a huge thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.localizationlab.org/&quot;&gt;Localization Lab&lt;/a&gt; and their network of expert volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note that we are very close to connecting the SAFETAG repository directly with the Transifex platform to streamline the translation process moving forward.  &lt;strong&gt;SAFETAG welcomes new content in any language.&lt;/strong&gt; If you want to create new content in our current non-English languages or add content in a new language, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:info@SAFETAG.org&quot;&gt;info@SAFETAG.org&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/issues&quot;&gt;submit an issue&lt;/a&gt; so we can help get it set up.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The challenges of reporting: Reporting Styles]]></title><description><![CDATA[This article was written by Carlos Guerra with the input and help of
Mario Felaco; of Conexo. See part 1: The Challenges of Reporting Said…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2018-11-20-challenges-of-reporting-2</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2018-11-20-challenges-of-reporting-2</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 15:12:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was written by Carlos Guerra with the input and help of
Mario Felaco; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://conexo.org/&quot;&gt;Conexo&lt;/a&gt;. See part 1: &lt;a href=&quot;https://SAFETAG.org/2018/11/19/challenges-of-reporting.html&quot;&gt;The Challenges of Reporting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Said this, some of the kind of reports I&apos;ve seen in my evaluations and
from others work are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;1: The magic recipe oriented report&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/challengesreporting/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simple, short and sometimes effective, usually this kind of reports have
a short list of actions the organization needs to do to improve their
security, sometimes this list is divided in immediate, short, medium and
large term. the actions can be as short or detailed as we want them to
be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the organization gave you only a few days to assess them they will have 5 minutes to read this list&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the organization talks the same language as us at the end of the assessment this kind of report will speed up the implementation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is fast to built so we can help the organization to implement security measures right away&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations not linked to the threat model so the organization isn&apos;t aware of the importance of the recommendations and the order&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does not build the organization’s own agency in understanding or mitigating their risks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could be confusing if the actions are not clear for the reader&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communicating technical things can be challenging and can cause the organization to dismiss recommendations just for not understanding them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally are bad for giving them to third parties giving the lack of detail&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s difficult for the organization to reproduce the results&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;2: The asset oriented report&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/challengesreporting/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The organization generally knows what assets they have, so it&apos;s
interesting to talk in a language they can understand easily&lt;/p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easy in terms of communication&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the risk of each asset they can assess what kind of recommendations they want to apply first, owning better the security process&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is easier to share part of the report with external consultants that usually work with specific types of assets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report is easy to collaborate on when there is more than one person running the assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the structure and detail level could be difficult for the organization to reproduce the results&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the structure and detail level could be challenging communicating technical things causing the organization to dismiss recommendations just for not understanding them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could be difficult to organize when similar assets have different threat models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could be difficult to link the specific assessment activities with the assets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could be difficult to organize visually assets vs. risk associated vs. implementation terms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;3: The activity oriented report&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/challengesreporting/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another way we can order the information of the assessment is in
function of the specific activities we run during the assessment. This
usually leads to specify well which tools or indicators were used,
making it a nice input for IT staff and consultants linked with the
organization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allows us to build the report faster because we can feed this kind of report as a log during the process&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could be intuitive for technical audiences. Useful when the organization have IT staff and they are the most involved part during the assessment. With this format is easier for them to reproduce the results&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to do more activities during the process is more intuitive to add the new information to the report&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report is easy to feed by more than one people running the assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally not the most intuitive format for the organizations given that they could not be familiar with our activities/tools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the structure and detail level could be challenging communicating technical things causing the organization to dismiss recommendations just for not understanding them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could be difficult to organize visually activities vs. assets vs. risk associated vs. implementation terms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t work as well for assessments that go beyond the more specific technical aspects -- it is hard to bring in higher level (policy, practice) problems which do not cleanly “fit” in any one activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;4: The super comprehensive (and sometimes dangerously long) risk oriented report&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/blog/challengesreporting/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This approach without doubt is the more complete on this article, it
aims to catalogue and develop 4 types of information:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threats:&lt;/strong&gt; coming principally from the threat modelling activity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vulnerabilities:&lt;/strong&gt; discovered during the execution of the assessment activities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendations:&lt;/strong&gt; developed to respond to the vulnerabilities discovered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implementation plan:&lt;/strong&gt; ordering the recommendations in a way that makes sense for the organization&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can have better results with this approach when we can link the
vulnerabilities with the associated threats and with the correspondent
recommendations, so if we are reading a recommendation we can know what
vulnerabilities and threats it tries to address. Giving the reader the
most important answers she/he needs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given the complexity of this approach is crucial to select a structure
and format that makes easy to the reader reach the information he/she
wants to get without distracting with noise, this could be particularly
challenging when using formats like PDFs or odt/docx.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually everything you want to know about the assessment is on the report, facilitating the understanding of the organization especially when in the future it will be more difficult to contact us&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guarantees that the assessors are linking suggestions to identified threats and organizational priorities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It links directly the group exercise made during the assessment with the recommendations, making it easier for the organization to understand the pertinence of them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follows an ordered process, leading an open door to automation (spoiler: working on that :wink: )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It helps the organization to keep an eye on the evolution of their threat model while implementing the recommendations, making the organization an active part in the process of follow-up and opens a door to do a better Monitoring and Evaluation of the security implementation process&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could be overwhelming to write and overwhelming to read if the format is not clear and ordered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Takes a long time to build (Careful with the need of the organization to start working fast on security measures)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could take long time to read (Again careful with formats, if someone needs/wants to read just 5% of the report help her/him to reach quickly and effectively to that 5%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This format requires running the threat modelling activities from SAFETAG (Which in my opinion should be the norm, but it could affect your freedom selecting the activities)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;5: The awesome format that you use and we don&apos;t know... yet&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding that there is no silver bullet for reporting security
assessments for NGOs and independent media outlets, we can open the
discussion about many other ways to present the information we gather
during our assessments. If you know and/or use another approach and want
to share it with this community, don&apos;t doubt to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;With all of this options and the potential combinations and variations
of them, it&apos;s virtually impossible to not have one kind of report that
adapts well to our needs in each case. In our case, we usually aim for
the long report in point 4 given that the information gathered for it
allows us to rewrite the report to be more like the simpler versions
described above. The more experience you have as an auditor, the faster
you will become at identifying what type of report the organization will
be able to understand the best, even if you yourself are still
conceptualizing and seeking out the answers as if you were building the
most comprehensive report. For instance: if the organization explicitly
wants something short, they are in a bad moment in terms of security and
they need to implement fast, we want to give a detailed report for
IT/Management and another shorter for the Directors or for some external
technical service provider; we already have everything we need. Once
again, is up to you (mostly) what kind of report do you want to build
and what kind of report the organization you attend needs, just remember
that &lt;em&gt;our ultimate goal is that they understand how secure they are and
implement measures to improve their security and do a better job&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The challenges of reporting]]></title><description><![CDATA[*This article was written by Carlos Guerra with the input and help of
Mario Felaco; of Con-nexo. * We run organizational security training…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2018-11-19-challenges-of-reporting</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2018-11-19-challenges-of-reporting</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 18:12:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;*This article was written by Carlos Guerra with the input and help of
Mario Felaco; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://con-nexo.org/&quot;&gt;Con-nexo&lt;/a&gt;. *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We run organizational security training sessions, long term support and
security assessments for NGOs (Non-Government Organizations) and
independent media outlets at risk in Latin America. We base a lot of of
our work on the SAFETAG framework and we like to promote it to new
people that want to help organizations improve their security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As previously said in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://safetag.org/2018/08/16/SAFETAGStories-dropbox.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;SAFETAG Stories: If you fail -- TRI, TRI
Again&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
there isn&apos;t one unique approach on security assessments for
organizations and independent media outlets; their unique structures and
dynamics make it difficult to assume there is a single way to evaluate
security or even a single way they can respond to our recommendations.
After a few years doing SAFETAG-based assessments and security
interventions, I&apos;ve come across different ways that I and others end up
building assessment reports. They can be widely different, without
meaning that one report style is wrong or right. It is just a matter of
knowing when is more convenient to use one approach or another. Some of
the factors that can affect what kind of information and how much of it
the organization could digest are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presence of IT staff that want to understand the vulnerability gathering process:&lt;/strong&gt; This is usually to reproduce it in the future so they can confirm your findings and assess changes after applying the recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical skill level of the organization and targets of the report:&lt;/strong&gt; In some cases you can skip the explanation of some concepts and go straight to the results, in others it can be  useful to explain the basic concepts in the same report.  Personally I don&apos;t like the idea of giving recommendations that the organization won&apos;t implement just because they don&apos;t understand anything about the acronyms and 1s and 0s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capacity and time to read/learn about everything:&lt;/strong&gt; Organizations that just don&apos;t have the time to read a report about something not directly related to they main work (Human rights, investigative journalism, you name it) are the norm, so being super concise and having them read just what they need to know is a very valid approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transfer of implementation responsibility to someone different from the target of the report:&lt;/strong&gt; If the targets of the report aren’t the final implementers of the recommendations, things can get complicated. “Encrypt the data on the computers” can suffice for some targets (specially if you’ve had conversations and what you suggest is implicit), but if an external consultant reads that it would completely valid to wonder “mmm... with veracrypt? with GPG? inside zips? the whole hard drives?” and perhaps think your report sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Debrief and follow up opportunities:&lt;/strong&gt; A chance to walk through the report with the organization helps lower the report “learning curve”, giving you some leeway to make them more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, some aspects that could affect the report building in
our side of the fence are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; We need to know that we can build the report in an appropriate amount of time. If we just have a couple of days it could be super difficult to write something more comprehensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requirements:&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes the people that ask for our help already have an idea of what they want. In that case the only advice would be to adapt to that idea as long as it is feasible with the resources allocated and the kind of work that we can do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our personal taste:&lt;/strong&gt; Let&apos;s face it, some people aren&apos;t the talking type of person, others want to communicate it all. It’s ok for that to affect the kind of report you’re building, as long as the report is useful and pertinent for the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing to remember is our final goal: that the organizations in fact enhance their security, not just going through a checklist and leave them on their own. Whichever form the reports takes, it should always strive towards that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With that in mind, on the next post we&apos;ll talk about some of the types of reports we&apos;ve done and seen others do.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SAFETAG Stories: The DDoS Outreach Strategy]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is the third in a series of blog posts sharing some stories gleaned from audits over the years (often combined from multiple…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2018-08-24-SAFETAGStories-ddosoutreach</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2018-08-24-SAFETAGStories-ddosoutreach</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2018 15:49:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the third in a series of blog posts sharing some stories gleaned from audits over the years (often combined from multiple experiences and with all identifying information removed).  The goal is to share experiences and approaches to help new auditors get into the mindset of SAFETAG&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAFETAG Stories: The DDoS Outreach Strategy
The SAFETAG framework emphasizes the importance of putting the organization first, and helping them prioritize their own risks. This often feels at odds with more traditional, prescriptive approaches to security audits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAFETAG itself began as a way to adapt professional &quot;penetration testing&quot; to the NGO world. To say that we learned a lot along the way would be a colossal understatement. Penetration tests are fantastic for, well, organizations with an IT team and a large budget. If your organization&apos;s focus is to support independent media, support vulnerable populations, or advance other social good outcomes, your budget is (sadly) more limited, and your IT support is stretched to capacity in just keeping systems functional and staff supported through some of the most amazingly creative tricks possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To balance the real threats organizations face with the constraints of time, staff and budget they are under, SAFETAG focuses on empowering organizations to explore their own tolerance for risk, where they face risk, and how they might mitigate or reduce it in a way that respects their mission and capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple example would be an organization which depends on individual donations through its website.  The reputation of the organization, the safety and reliability of its donation system, and the protection of the identities and credit card or banking information of its donors is paramount to that organization&apos;s ongoing success.  They may have many odd, not-perfect systems, but if they have an outdated website with well-known vulnerabilities and no clear website management plan, finding an affordable solution may be the first priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite actual example from an audit was working with a media and transparency organization. Among many challenges they faced, one stood out as unusually simple to fix --  their website got reliably DDoSed and taken down every time they released a new, impactful report. We immediately suggested the free DDoS protection Deflect.ca provides for media and human rights tools. The organization politely declined, and explained that every time they got DDoS’ed, they would go onto various social media platforms to complain about that, which ended up driving more interest in their reports.  Intentionally allowing one’s site to get attacked like that may sound crazy on the surface, but for this organization at the time it was part of their outreach strategy, and it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic of SAFETAG is not technical magic, hacker tools that would be at home in Mr. Robot, Black Mirror, or the Matrix, and it&apos;s not expensive tools. The magic of SAFETAG is listening to the organization you&apos;re working with, understanding the context they operate in, and helping to make sure their practices match the threats they face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work is scary, difficult, impossible, unending, and more -- but at the same time, it is also challenging in the best way. Actually listening to an organization and providing pragmatic, achievable next steps for improved organizational security is the most challenging - and rewarding - part of being an auditor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s easy to simply state that they need professional IT and security support. It&apos;s easy to mandate that they never again open an attachment. It&apos;s unrealistic for this to happen. We do not operate in an ideal, unconstrained world.  Budgets are not infinite -- if they even exist.  Threats are real and have very real impacts where the above example of losing online donations pale in comparison to some of the alternatives, yet there are real limits to what can be done.  A five-person journalism outfit is not going to hire a 100k USD infosec expert and an IT team to manage their online presence -- and they cannot simply stop opening sketchy attachments people email them promising juicy scoops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But. But maybe that outdated website could be protected behind a service like Cloudflare (or better, Deflect), and maybe they can transition their email to Google, and use Google Drive to open attachments first.  It may not be a techno-utopia, (and these are not universal recommendations! Your mileage may vary!) but the impact on their security, in a way that respects their needs and their capacity - is worth it.  Imperfect but positive first steps can lead to a better culture of security within the organization, and grow their capacity to move to more advanced solutions while keeping them safer in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SAFETAG Stories: The Forgotten Incident]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is the second in a series of blog posts sharing some stories gleaned from audits over the years (often combined from multiple…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2018-08-20-SAFETAGStories-forgottenincident</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2018-08-20-SAFETAGStories-forgottenincident</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 12:49:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the second in a series of blog posts sharing some stories gleaned from audits over the years (often combined from multiple experiences and with all identifying information removed).  The goal is to share experiences and approaches to help new auditors get into the mindset of SAFETAG&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/08/16/SAFETAGStories-dropbox.html&quot;&gt;previous SAFETAG Story&lt;/a&gt;, we explained the “TRI” approach in choosing activities which take different approaches (&lt;strong&gt;Technical&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Research&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Interpersonal&lt;/strong&gt;) in order to TRI-angulate (!!!) the reality of what is going on at an organization. That variety is critical, but sometimes not enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even within one category, sometimes one approach just doesn’t work with the organization. The activity may be geared towards a small group, but the organization is large. It may expect people to be in one room, but the organization is distributed across locations and even time zones. Sometimes, it may just not work for reasons that are not clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The Forgotten incident&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;At one audit, the audit team had gone through the normal motions of process mapping, talking about potential adversaries, ranking what risks and their impacts were not acceptable, as well as research around digital challenges faced in their country and around their issue area. After almost a week, we had simply not found any specific concerns beyond the normal outdated computers and network glitches, and were looking forward to a simple and straightforward audit findings and recommendations reporting process.  SAFETAG recommends having some form of “debrief” at the end of every audit, to respect concerns and provide one last point of contact and reassurance to staff. During this, someone casually mentioned a theft from a few years back, where only the hard drives of the computers were stolen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That… is an odd and very specific thing to steal. We had to have additional conversations to re-scope and re-prioritize some of the recommendations we had planned on providing, as well as re-think what threats this organization was actually facing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a great example of a situation where multiple activities theoretically &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have caught this -- from initial interviews with management and technical staff, to idle chatter during &quot;Day in the Life&quot; style direct engagement with staff members, or any of the group activities such as process mapping, data mapping, or in particular some of the risk rating exercises where the organization discusses previous incidents.  An important lesson here is that while it can sometimes feel like you are repeating work or returning to questions you think you have the answers to, it can be the only way you uncover critical information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SAFETAG Stories: If you fail -- TRI, TRI Again]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is the first in a series of blog posts sharing some stories gleaned from audits over the years (often combined from multiple…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2018-08-16-SAFETAGStories-dropbox</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2018-08-16-SAFETAGStories-dropbox</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2018 12:49:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the first in a series of blog posts sharing some stories gleaned from audits over the years (often combined from multiple experiences and with all identifying information removed).  The goal is to share experiences and approaches to help new auditors get into the mindset of SAFETAG&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most common questions we get about the SAFETAG framework is whether one has to do everything in it for it to “count” as an assessment based on SAFETAG.  The answer is &lt;strong&gt;absolutely not&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In describing SAFETAG, I often poke fun at the inevitable result of traditional &quot;penetration tests&quot; against an organization.  These tests try every handle, press every button, and push on every closed door of an organization&apos;s digital (and often physical) security to map out every possible vulnerability, resulting in incredibly detailed and overwhelming reports. For many organizations, this report may not even include a clear way to prioritize how to tackle it beyond a gazillion &quot;high&quot; priority issues and countless &quot;medium&quot; and below things to also ponder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The secret follow-up punchline however, is that SAFETAG itself is, well, an overwhelming, detailed, 300+ page behemoth itself, and will continue to grow.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Choose your own SAFETAG Adventure: Try out the &quot;TRI&quot; model&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are working to make working with SAFETAG feel as flexible as it was built to be. It has always been a modular, &quot;choose-your-own-adventure&quot; style approach to working closely with organizations to assess the risks they face, and the best path for addressing their top priorities. One important way we are doing this is by adding metadata into each activity to help auditors build a comprehensive audit plan (follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/tree/metadata&quot;&gt;metadata branch at https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/tree/metadata&lt;/a&gt;  and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/issues/334%5D&quot;&gt;issue at https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/issues/334&lt;/a&gt;!  Initially, we are focusing on the time each activity takes, specific skills it requires, and what “type” of activity it is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In SAFETAG, the various activities we suggest to learn about an organization tend to fall in three broad approaches: &lt;strong&gt;Technical&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Research&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Interpersonal&lt;/strong&gt;. It is tempting to focus on the style of approach you as the auditor are most comfortable with - people with backgrounds in digital security training tend towards the interpersonal, people with pentesting backgrounds the technical. However, by using a combination of these, you get a clearer understanding of not only the organization’s setup and infrastructure, but how decisions are made, how policies are enforced (or not), and where there are opportunities for organizational change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;The Dropbox Effect&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;An illustrative story from my own auditing experience is what I call the “dropbox effect”. This story, with small changes, has come out of … many audits I’ve been a part of. It starts during the initial scoping and interviewing stage (&lt;em&gt;Interpersonal&lt;/em&gt;!), where management and/or any technical staff will say something to the effect that the organization has made a decision to not use dropbox (or google drive, etc.), so no one is using it.  Digging through provided policy documents (&lt;em&gt;Research&lt;/em&gt;!), there may even be a section on correct storage and backup / filesharing for the organization which specifically bans dropbox.  Once you start scanning networks (&lt;em&gt;Technical&lt;/em&gt;!) and talking 1:1 with end users (&lt;em&gt;Interpersonal&lt;/em&gt; again!) as you sit with them and look at their desktop systems (&lt;em&gt;Technical&lt;/em&gt; again!) -- a different picture emerges.  Dropbox is &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, research and initial interpersonal approaches lead you to expect that staff members are not using dropbox.  Additional activities (in this case, mostly technical) reveal the exact opposite.  The combination of this work will reveal the why.  Perhaps the communications lead needs to regularly send very large files to a print shop, and dropbox works where email doesn’t and SBs are unsafe. Perhaps people are using it to sync family or pet photos from their home account to have as a screensaver. Perhaps some people simply never uninstalled it after the policy change, but aren’t actively using it.  Any or all of these can provide a hint towards what a recommendation to resolve this difference between the organization’s policies and its actual practices.  Based on the specific risks and priorities of the organization, it may be relaxing the “dropbox ban” and improving information controls and entry/exit policies instead, or actually enforcing it but finding workable, policy-compliant solutions for these specific cases.

&lt;strong&gt;Does the TRI concept make sense? Sound even more confusing? Let us know on the issue queue or at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:info@safetag.org&quot;&gt;info@safetag.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Updates from the Advanced Threats Workshop!]]></title><description><![CDATA[SAFETAG Fellows and partners gathered for a 3-day workshop to expand the guidance that the SAFETAG framework has for auditors to respond to…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2018-05-04-Advanced_Threats</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2018-05-04-Advanced_Threats</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 12:49:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;SAFETAG Fellows and partners gathered for a 3-day workshop to expand the guidance that the SAFETAG framework has for auditors to respond to advanced threats - organizations receiving phishing emails or with active malware in their systems. This will all be included in a release going live later today.  Thanks to all the contributions and support from the fellows in creating this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Responding to Advanced Threats Method&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In advance of the workshop, Dlshad Othman put together a new SAFETAG method for advanced threat response paired with an analysis activity. At the workshop, we expanded this into a full-on triage approach for responding to attacks, paired with  &quot;hooks&quot; across the framework to better identify signs of active attacks.  This collection of changes makes heavy use of the activity &quot;variant&quot; approach to combine very similar or parallel approaches in one single activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The majority of the work can be found in the new &lt;strong&gt;&quot;Responding to Advanced Threats&quot;&lt;/strong&gt; method and its related activities, detailed below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is important to underline that this is focused on identifying malicious activity and doing the minimal possible analysis to responsibly triage it. Deeper analysis of the specifics may happen during the report-writing phase, but it is important to not be easily derailed from completing the SAFETAG audit process.  This drives home the importance of having an agreed-upon incident response plan with the organization to determine how they would prefer to respond if something that is potentially serious occurs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;New and Updated Activities&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Identifying and Analyzing Suspicious Activities&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Malware is a common tactic to target organizations, Malwares like RAT (Remote Access Trojan) can provide an attacker with a back-door access to a targeted machine which enables the attacker to steal information, record audio and video and run commands on the infected machine. This component provides an overview for analyzing different types of suspicious emails, files, active processes, and network traffic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Evidence Capture&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;This component briefs the tools and procedures required to acquire the image (live or dead, depending on the situation) and securely handle data from a device (laptop, desktop, HDD, memory stick, USB stick, etc.) that is needed to later perform a malware analysis or forensic evidence process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Digital Forensics&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;This component describes how to perform an analysis on captured evidence (e.g. hard drive image or memory dump) without altering the evidence. Any alteration, or even an environment or situation that creates the possibility of alteration, could lead to rejection of the evidence in a court of law or to malware analysis failures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In most cases, reach out for help, there are multiple organizations which coordinate and can support malware analysis targeting NGOs. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://rarenet.github.io/DFAK/en/SecureCommunication/&quot;&gt;Digital First Aid Kit&lt;/a&gt; has a list of organizations and in most cases secure contact details to seek support in doing advanced analysis. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rarenet.org/&quot;&gt;Rapid Response Network&lt;/a&gt;, a project of &lt;a href=&quot;https://civicert.org/&quot;&gt;CiviCERT&lt;/a&gt; is a consortia of these organizations who may be able to help. &lt;a href=&quot;https://citizenlab.ca/&quot;&gt;Citizen Lab&lt;/a&gt; is also well known for their analysis and research.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Technical Context Research&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;An important cornerstone in working with high-risk organizations is having an expansive understanding of their potential adversaries and their capabilities. This has long been guidance in SAFETAG, and at the workshop we pushed out a more structured approach to tackle this research based on Internews&apos; internal digital country risk assessment methodology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Changes to Incident Response&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since its inception, SAFETAG has had a section instructing auditors to create an agreed-upon incident response plan with the organization.  During the Advanced Threats workshop, we expanded on this in parallel with the overall &quot;triage&quot; approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Changes to the Interview activity and creation of a High-Risk Interview activity&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the pre-audit interview process, we have improved the formatting of the overall section and added more questions to help identify potential attacks, and added a specific &quot;Guiding Questions for High-Risk Organisations&quot; to dive deeper where the auditor and/or organization already suspects they are under active attack. This additional interview activity is to identify if there are any indicators that the organization may have already been attacked and/or compromised, or if someone they know has faced advanced threats. It should help identify what threats / threat actors they are dealing with, and their intent. This will help the auditor prioritize work with the organisation during the audit and follow up and understand whether the auditor has the expertise to address or understand the threat or if outside expertise is needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Changes to Network Scanning and Traffic Analysis&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have added some guidance to help auditors judge whether open ports and network traffic is out of the ordinary for office environments. Naturally, every office set up is different, and this will rely on the auditor conducting on-site research and analysis.  These changes are in the Network Scanning and Traffic Analysis activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SAFETAG Contribution Templates!]]></title><description><![CDATA[Thanks to some feedback, we've updated the contribution guide at CONTRIBUTING.md with clearer, step-by-step guides, a reminder to post an…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2017-11-18-templates</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2017-11-18-templates</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2017 17:49:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to some feedback, we&apos;ve updated the contribution guide at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/blob/master/en/document_matter/CONTRIBUTING.md&quot;&gt;CONTRIBUTING.md&lt;/a&gt; with clearer, step-by-step guides, a reminder to post an issue to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/issues&quot;&gt;issue queue&lt;/a&gt; first, and - most usefully - templates to use to get started crafting new SAFETAG methods and activities.  Those can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/tree/master/en/templates&quot;&gt;templates folder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[REMINDER: Nov 17 deadline for SAFETAG Fellowship Grants ]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internews is launching a funding pool to diversify and scale SAFETAG across the broader human rights and digital security community…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2017-09-30-safetagfellowship</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2017-09-30-safetagfellowship</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2017 08:58:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Internews is launching a funding pool to diversify and scale SAFETAG across the broader human rights and digital security community. Internews is seeking to fund 10-12 individuals or teams embedded in organizations to customize SAFETAG to meet their needs, conduct SAFETAG-based assessments integrating these customizations, and share these approaches back with the SAFETAG community. Grant amounts are expected to vary based on local costs and scope, but the average grant is expected to be $25,000 USD and approximately 4 months in duration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winning applications must support at least two SAFETAG-based assessments of at-risk organizations working with vulnerable or marginalized communities. These assessments should be in parallel with the creation and documentation of customized approaches -- new activities which work better for the applicant&apos;s region/community/specific threats and/or a &quot;playlist&quot; of existing (and custom-created or modified) SAFETAG activities which best work for this community. Grantees will be expected to responsibly share the non-identifying context research (e.g. high-level country risk assessments) within the SAFETAG community and to coordinate on peer-training events to share their approach. Following each assessment, the grantee will help the recipient organization develop risk mitigation plans to address weaknesses, and either provide direct support through existing organizational programming or connect the organization to external services, goods, or funding support as needed to address their security vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this entire process, the grantee will have ongoing access and mentoring from Internews’ SAFETAG team and access to the combination of skills and implementation expertise of the entire fellowship pool. Internews will work to &quot;match-make&quot; grantees working on similar or related challenges for peer-training opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preference will be towards individuals embedded in organizations working in the human rights and digital security space. Individuals may also apply, but the funding mechanism may be different. Winning applications will demonstrate continued post-funding usage of and contribution to SAFETAG as a community project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications are due &lt;strong&gt;November 17&lt;/strong&gt; and will be evaluated by Internews&apos; SAFETAG team, the SAFETAG Community Advisory Board, and in consultation with SAFETAG funders according to the criteria (and regulations) in the submission form. If funds permit a second round will be opened in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please submit your applications via this &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSco5cTEk1hArLMb86t4c2aZbuxLa5k40C3_dQxuRBYNGKjFeg/viewform?usp=sf_link&quot;&gt;Google Form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would prefer to submit this information via PGP, please send to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jon@safetag.org&quot;&gt;jon@safetag.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:afowler@internews.org&quot;&gt;afowler@internews.org&lt;/a&gt;, encrypting to these keys: &lt;a href=&quot;http://pgp.mit.edu/pks/lookup?op=vindex&amp;#x26;search=0xB46A01C3270C17F1&quot;&gt;http://pgp.mit.edu/pks/lookup?op=vindex&amp;#x26;search=0xB46A01C3270C17F1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://pgp.mit.edu/pks/lookup?op=get&amp;#x26;search=0x6316FC03DF318F76&quot;&gt;http://pgp.mit.edu/pks/lookup?op=get&amp;#x26;search=0x6316FC03DF318F76&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[SAFETAG Agreement Generator]]></title><description><![CDATA[Seamus Tuohy of Prudent Innovation has completed an in-depth decision tree program for auditors/assessors to answer questions and builds a…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2017-10-10-agreementgenerator</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2017-10-10-agreementgenerator</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 16:49:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Seamus Tuohy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://prudentinnovation.org/&quot;&gt;Prudent Innovation&lt;/a&gt; has completed an in-depth decision tree program for auditors/assessors to answer questions and builds a detailed, plain language agreement for you to use in your engagements. It&apos;s built in Python on Debian/Ubuntu, and available &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/safetag/safetag_agreement_generator&quot;&gt;in the SAFETAG community github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It allows auditors to provide custom fee schedules and has specific call-outs for parts of the agreement which are the most critical to have local legal advice on. Given that SAFETAG auditors operate in legal jurisdictions all over the world and in a variety of languages, the template text will focused on clarity and conciseness instead of legalese. By clearly articulating the scope and intent of the each component lawyers in different regions will be able to evaluate and update the language to support their legal code. The repository comes with an example plain language template. It includes a &quot;base&quot; outline template and a fine-grained template file that extends this base. By editing the base template a assessor can add/remove large sections of the agreement without searching through the fine-grained template for the text they wish to remove, which also customizes the interactive agreement process, enabling auditors to quickly re-generate new agreements with small modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/safetag_agreement_generator/blob/master/README.md&quot;&gt;README file&lt;/a&gt; includes both an installation guide as well as usage and advance customization documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/seamustuohy/safetag_agreement_generator/raw/decision_tree/images/screenshot.png?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Agreement Generator Screenshot&quot; title=&quot;Agreement Generator Screenshot&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please test it out and send in feedback via the issue queue, as this will be replacing the existing &quot;draft engagement agreement&quot; currently in SAFETAG.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Contributing to SAFETAG -- and an Updated Guide!]]></title><description><![CDATA[As more and more contributors are helping build SAFETAG, we realized that the existing guidance on the structure had fallen out of line with…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2017-09-12-contributions</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2017-09-12-contributions</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 17:35:15 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;As more and more contributors are helping build SAFETAG, we realized that the existing guidance on the structure had fallen out of line with the current setup, and how the SAFETAG content is getting mapped into the Content as Code framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have now updated and combined our disparate documentation on the structure of SAFETAG in light of recent feedback and (in the ongoing effort to polish the repository) have uploaded it as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/blob/master/en/document_matter/CONTRIBUTING.md&quot;&gt;CONTRIBUTING.md file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there&apos;s an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/releases/tag/v0.4.1&quot;&gt;updated release&lt;/a&gt; (ironically not including the above documents yet) which rolls up the changes from the recent write-sprint.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Remote SAFETAG Assessments?]]></title><description><![CDATA[An ongoing interest in the SAFETAG community has been how to use the SAFETAG framework in situations where the auditor cannot travel to the…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2017-08-31-Remote_Audits</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2017-08-31-Remote_Audits</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2017 13:09:25 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;An ongoing interest in the SAFETAG community has been how to use the SAFETAG framework in situations where the auditor cannot travel to the organization at all, or cannot travel to remote or multiple office locations -- what can be done remotely, what can be done with help, and what gaps remain that must be accommodated? Thanks to coordination and co-funding with multiple organizations, a SAFETAG peer-training and content sprint answered these questions with new approaches and adaptations to support a variety of remote-only SAFETAG assessment work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Content created from this training and content sprint is included with summaries below and has been compiled into an updated &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/releases/tag/v0.4.1&quot;&gt;SAFETAG release&lt;/a&gt;.  The content sprint approach taken with this event took advantage of the existing expertise and experience of the attendees to co-create new approaches as a peer training approach.  This has the exciting add-on benefit of supporting community-sourced contributions on the SAFETAG github repository, which can be seen via the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/pulls?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;#x26;q=is%3Apr&quot;&gt;github commit and pull history&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Operational Security (expanded from Physical Security)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The thought process for dealing with &quot;remote&quot; audits - as well as the multiple scenarios they would be most likely - also led to improved clarity on the future of the &quot;Physical Security&quot; module for SAFETAG. It has been transformed into an &quot;Operational Security&quot; section to also include activities to determine staff traveling, working remotely or from home, and the security impacts of multiple offices, especially in situations where the auditor can only assess a subset of an organization&apos;s offices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The organizational security methodology is focused on how to mitigate against threats that occur because of the arrangement of digital assets in the physical world -- how secure are the devices at an organization&apos;s office, where and how staff travel with organizational devices, and whether staff work outside of the office (e.g. in remote offices, at their homes, while traveling, or at cafes).  Further, is organizational information accessed from personal devices, and how are those devices secured?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/pull/282&quot;&gt;Pull #282&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/issues/268&quot;&gt;Issue #268&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This also enabled the movement of some odd pieces of the framework inside of this, such as hands off discovery of wifi networks and device beacons/probes (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/pull/289&quot;&gt;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/pull/289&lt;/a&gt;) -- transforming an awkward &quot;module&quot; into an activity underneath this module that fits more naturally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Office Mapping (New)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This activity seeks to identify potential physical vulnerabilities to an organization&apos;s information security practices by documenting the current physical layout of the office and the locations of key assets, as well as potential &quot;external&quot; risks such as nearby/shared office spaces.  This can be done in person independently or alongside the &quot;Guided Tour&quot; activity, and can also be done in advance of an assessment or remotely by a willing staff member who knows where these assets are located (often a technical or administrative staff person). This can also be conducted in a multi-office or home-office environment where the auditor is unable to visit every location.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Guided Tour (Adapted to include remote support)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;During this component an auditor tours the audit location(s) and flags potential risks related to physical access at that location. This can be done remotely via secure videoconference over a smartphone or tablet that can moved around the office easily. Combining this activity with Office Mapping helps to reduce the awkwardness of taking notes while walking around the office, and if being done remotely, the two separate activities can be used to cross-verify the accuracy of each.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/pull/286&quot;&gt;Pull #286&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Scavenger Hunt (New)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This activity assists in identifying potential physical security concerns at an organization, particularly when an auditor cannot travel to the office location or cannot visit every office location. The scavenger hunt approach is focused on involving the organization staff members into mapping out potential threats based on the abstraction and the gamification of the physical security mapping process. See the &quot;Risk Hunting&quot; exercise in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.internews.org/sites/default/files/resources/SaferJournoGuide_2014-03-21.pdf&quot;&gt;SaferJourno&lt;/a&gt;, page 19, for additional ideas and guidance on conducting this activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Remote Local Network Scanning and  Device Assessment (Adapted)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This allows the auditor to work remotely to identify the devices on a host&apos;s network, the services that are being used by those devices, and any protections in place, as well as to assess the security of the individual devices on the network.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/pull/283&quot;&gt;Pull #283&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Remote Facilitation (New)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Suggested approaches and methods to use if in-person facilitation for activities such as process mapping and data assessment is not possible. This may not provide as deep results as in-person facilitation, but should provide adequate level of expansion and verification needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/pull/288&quot;&gt;Pull #288&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Shape the Future of SAFETAG]]></title><description><![CDATA[We are exploring how to better present the SAFETAG content and enable auditors to explore, build and share audit plans, and contribute back…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2017-08-09-Survey</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2017-08-09-Survey</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2017 12:09:25 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;We are exploring how to better present the SAFETAG content and enable auditors to explore, build and share audit plans, and contribute back to SAFETAG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please fill out this survey and inform the next steps of converting the content of SAFETAG into a more interactive and usable structure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.surveymonkey.de/r/G5Q5BF6&quot;&gt;https://www.surveymonkey.de/r/G5Q5BF6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Code of Conduct and Community Governance]]></title><description><![CDATA[Based on the work from Berlin and revisions and feedback since, we have an updated and streamlined SAFETAG community governance document…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2017-06-14-CodeofConduct</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2017-06-14-CodeofConduct</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 14:32:17 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Based on the work from Berlin and revisions and feedback since, we have an updated and streamlined SAFETAG community governance document!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find it, alongside the Code of Conduct in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SAFETAG/SAFETAG/blob/master/en/document_matter/CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md&quot;&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt; file in the github repository, which contains the mission, community standards, and community governance structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes the code of conduct to better more specific, revised the community standards to reflect that the SAFETAG community is living within the orgsec.community world, and simplified the Advisory Board language to get things rolling sooner. As this becomes a self-sustained consortia, we can expand and codify additional items as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Meet us at the Internet Freedom Festival next week!]]></title><description><![CDATA[SAFETAG continues to expand its adoption among groups doing organizational security work. Towards this, we joined with a group of 1…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2016-02-25-safetag-at-iff</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2016-02-25-safetag-at-iff</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 12:09:25 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;SAFETAG continues to expand its adoption among groups doing organizational security work. Towards this, we joined with a group of 15 practitioners recently in Prague who are working on all aspects of organizational security, from the audit/assessment piece through to implementation and follow-up support. We all shared experiences, resources and approaches to address our collective challenges by coalescing our understanding of what organizational security is, and how we can grow and hone our practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were all very encouraged and buoyed by the depth and breadth of the collective knowledge to be tapped, and resolved to use this as a launching pad towards a larger knowledge space and a community of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are attending the &lt;a href=&quot;https://internetfreedomfestival.org/&quot;&gt;Internet Freedom Festival&lt;/a&gt;, we invite you to join the discussion, hear our outline of how to grow as an independent, open, and collaborative community; and if you are interested, to join efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an initial session Thursday March 3 Noon-1 focused on building a more collaborative assessment framework based out of SAFETAG, followed up by an all-morning session scheduled for Friday 10–1, March 4. We want to hear from you about the challenges you face implementing organizational security support and your solutions; about your own organizational security systems and practices; and how you could benefit and contribute as an active member of this growing community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Dubrovnik_ccBY_JonCamfield.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Dubrovnik Lock CC-BY Jon Camfield&quot; title=&quot;Dubrovnik Lock CC-BY Jon Camfield&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This comment has been adapted from a cross-organizational posting which has included the below people and organizations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ali G. Ravi, Confabium - &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@medialium/finally-some-good-news-about-organizational-security-9ac21e186e1d#.jnl6eukyv&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alix Dunn, the engine room - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theengineroom.org/finally-some-good-news-about-organizational-security/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CC, EngageMedia - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.engagemedia.org/blog/finally-some-good-news-about-organizational-security&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Friedhelm Weinberg, HURIDOCS - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huridocs.org/2016/02/improve-organizational-security-build-relationships-iff/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jon Camfield, SAFETAG/Internews - &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@joncamfield/a-quick-update-meet-us-at-the-internet-freedom-festival-next-week-d04d1d54727b&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Karel Novotný, APC - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apc.org/en/blog/finally-some-good-news-about-organizational-securi&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kody Leonard, The ISC Project - &lt;a href=&quot;https://iscproject.org/finally-some-good-news-about-organizational-security-2/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kristin Antin, the engine room - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theengineroom.org/finally-some-good-news-about-organizational-security/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maya Richman, the engine room - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theengineroom.org/finally-some-good-news-about-organizational-security/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michael Carbone, Access Now - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.accessnow.org/finally-some-good-news-about-organizational-security/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Natasha Msonza, Digital Society of Zimbabwe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Niels ten Oever, Article 19&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pablo Zavala, Front Line Defenders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter Steudtner, HIVOS-DIF / pantraining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wojtek Bogusz, Front Line Defenders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Meet SAFETAG: Helping Non-Profits Focus on Digital Security]]></title><description><![CDATA[Padlock CC-BY Rachel Titiriga/Flickr I’d be willing to wager that you, like me, have been offered “credit monitoring services” more than…]]></description><link>https://safetag.org/posts/2015-11-18-medium-meet-safetag</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://safetag.org/posts/2015-11-18-medium-meet-safetag</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2015 12:09:25 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Flickr_Padlock_ccBY_pocait-Rachel-Titiriga.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Padlock CC-BY Rachel Titiriga/Flickr&quot; title=&quot;CC-BY Rachel-Titiriga/Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d be willing to wager that you, like me, have been offered “credit monitoring services” more than once in the past few years, because a place you’ve done business with or a past employer was hacked, potentially putting your personal data out on the market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporations and governments, while they are struggling to keep up with hacks, do have resources and teams devoted to the battle. But smaller, much more vulnerable victims of attacks deserve our attention too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-profit organizations around the world are also targeted by cybercrime, and don’t have the benefit of expensive services or personnel monitoring or protecting their systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it’s not as if these small organizations don’t have valuable information — from pre-published research to healthcare data, records of environmental transgressions to election monitoring procedures — development and civil society work around the world collects reams of information that, in the wrong hands, can put an organization or its beneficiaries at risk. Even a lost smartphone or laptop will contain contracts, financial data, and private conversations embedded in the constant steam of emails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizational security can feel like an impossible task, and many security audits or “penetration tests” are expensive and can be too aggressive for most small organizations. Vulnerabilities exist but fixing them are not necessarily high-priority for the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past two years, Internews has developed SAFETAG™ (Security Auditing Framework and Evaluation Template for Advocacy Groups) to address this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What is SAFETAG?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;SAFETAG provides a framework that a digital security expert can use to help organizations identify and prioritize the risks they face and suggest a tightly-focused path to mitigating them. This path to increased safety is designed to be responsive to the actual capacity of an organization. This last element is critical. We have learned that even the best-laid plans will go to waste if the organization is not capable of implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Audits based on the SAFETAG methodology start by working with the organization to explore the information and processes that they consider the most valuable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a media or journalism organization, for example, there might be calls and emails between a writer and confidential sources, which then turn into a working draft that is emailed between the author and editors before being sent to a webmaster to be added to the website. Are the phone calls sensitive? Should they be made over an encrypted connection? Where are the emails being stored? Work laptops? Personal smartphones? Email servers hosted by the organization?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The answers to each of these questions help the auditor and the organization think about where vulnerabilities that actually matter to the organization might be hiding. The process mixes interviews, exercises and technical verification and scanning, including documenting what the organization thinks it does versus what it actually does. The goal is to make all the organization’s processes and practices — not just the official ones — safe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, SAFETAG is like the stone soup parable — the deepest impact comes from the organization taking the time to reflect on the threats they realistically face, the danger this puts them in, and their capacity to reduce these risks over time. The auditor is a catalyst with the resources to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Radical Openness&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another way that SAFETAG differs from more traditional security audits is that the entire framework is open source and licensed for reuse and re-mixing. Even the trademark on the name “SAFETAG” is meant to encourage organizations to adapt and build on SAFETAG — it requires auditors to avoid calling their work a “SAFETAG audit” but instead use phrases more like “based on SAFETAG.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SAFETAG continues to evolve — as of today, Internews has trained 13 digital security auditors around the world and performed audits and risk assessments based upon the SAFETAG methodology for 20 at-risk organizations. More exciting than that, however, is organic uptake of the SAFETAG methodology. Other organizations are conducting their own versions of audits based upon SAFETAG.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The entire methodology is open and available on github, with active conversations around the future of the framework visible in the issues queue. “Compiled” versions of SAFETAG are available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.SAFETAG.org&quot;&gt;https://www.SAFETAG.org&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The future of SAFETAG is to drive — and be driven by — this cross-organizational adoption. Working with this community, Internews is creating a set of practices and a common language that make up the SAFETAG “core activities,” along with with a “plug-in” type approach for advanced SAFETAG topics that auditors can provide to help organizations work through not only digital security risks, but also financial, reputational, or even legal risks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interested? We’d love to see you over in our issue queue!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pocait/6974320264/&quot;&gt;Padlock: Plovdiv, Bulgaria -- Rachel Titiriga/CC-BY&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>